<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Microb Cell Fact</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Microbial Cell Factories</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1475-2859</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21092203</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3003633</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1475-2859-9-89</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1475-2859-9-89</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Physiological characteristics of the extreme thermophile <italic>Caldicellulosiruptor saccharolyticus</italic>: an efficient hydrogen cell factory</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1"><name><surname>Willquist</surname><given-names>Karin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>karin.willquist@tmb.lth.se</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Zeidan</surname><given-names>Ahmad A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>ahmad.zeidan@tmb.lth.se</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>van Niel</surname><given-names>Ed WJ</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>Ed.van_Niel@tmb.lth.se</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Applied Microbiology, Lund University, Getingev&#x000e4;gen 60, SE-222 41 Lund, Sweden</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>11</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>8</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>11</month><year>2010</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9;2010 Willquist et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Willquist et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (&#x0003c;url&#x0003e;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0&#x0003c;/url&#x0003e;), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.microbialcellfactories.com/content/9/1/89"/><abstract><p>Global concerns about climate changes and their association with the use of fossil fuels have accelerated research on biological fuel production. Biological hydrogen production from hemicellulose-containing waste is considered one of the promising avenues. A major economical issue for such a process, however, is the low substrate conversion efficiency. Interestingly, the extreme thermophilic bacterium <italic>Caldicellulosiruptor saccharolyticus </italic>can produce hydrogen from carbohydrate-rich substrates at yields close to the theoretical maximum of the dark fermentation process (i.e., 4 mol H<sub>2</sub>/mol hexose). The organism is able to ferment an array of mono-, di- and polysaccharides, and is relatively tolerant to high partial hydrogen pressures, making it a promising candidate for exploitation in a biohydrogen process. The behaviour of this Gram-positive bacterium bears all hallmarks of being adapted to an environment sparse in free sugars, which is further reflected in its low volumetric hydrogen productivity and low osmotolerance. These two properties need to be improved by at least a factor of 10 and 5, respectively, for a cost-effective industrial process. In this review, the physiological characteristics of <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>are analyzed in view of the requirements for an efficient hydrogen cell factory. A special emphasis is put on the tight regulation of hydrogen production in <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>by both redox and energy metabolism. Suggestions for strategies to overcome the current challenges facing the potential use of the organism in hydrogen production are also discussed.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>1. Introduction</title><p>Anthropogenic CO<sub>2 </sub>emissions have generally been recognized as the major contributor to global warming and associated climate changes. Therefore, several measures are being taken to decrease the CO<sub>2 </sub>emission. In recent years, much effort has been devoted to rendering biofuel production economically competitive to that of fossil fuels, since this will contribute significantly to the reduction of energy-linked environmental impacts. In this quest, the choice of the raw material is of central concern. First-generation biofuels are produced from sucrose and starch-rich substrates, which may compete with human consumption - inevitably driving up market prices. As a remedy, more focus should be directed to second-generation biofuels, produced from non-edible lignocellulosic materials, the most naturally abundant raw material [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>], as well as domestic and industrial wastes. The accompanying significant cost reductions should make biofuels more competitive.</p><p>Biohydrogen is a typical example of an environmentally friendly biofuel, with no CO<sub>2 </sub>emission resulting from its combustion. It can be produced from both lignocellulosic and waste materials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>], through biological conversion processes, such as dark fermentation and photofermentation. In the latter, biohydrogen can be produced using purple sulphur or non-sulphur bacteria that convert organic acids to H<sub>2 </sub>in photon-driven reactions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Although a combination of these two processes is an interesting approach for maximum conversion of the energy contained in carbohydrate-rich substrates into H<sub>2 </sub>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>], only dark fermentative H<sub>2 </sub>production is covered in this review.</p><p>In total, 12 H<sub>2 </sub>molecules can be obtained per mole of glucose, based on the overall number of electrons that can be generated in the complete oxidation of the latter. However, dark fermentation is limited to a maximum H<sub>2</sub>-production efficiency of 33%, i.e., maximally four molecules of H<sub>2 </sub>can be acquired per molecule of glucose with acetate and CO<sub>2 </sub>as the other fermentation end products [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Yet, this is only possible when the H<sub>2 </sub>partial pressure (<italic>P</italic><sub>H2</sub>) is kept adequately low [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>], e.g. by continuous stripping of the produced H<sub>2 </sub>with an inert gas. However, for a cost-effective dark fermentation process it is vital to obtain significantly high H<sub>2 </sub>yields at relatively elevated <italic>P</italic><sub>H2</sub>, due to the high impact of central costs of feedstock and gas upgrading [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Generally, mesophilic (co-)cultures reach H<sub>2 </sub>yields of &#x02264; 2 moles/mol hexose [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], thus exemplifying conversion efficiencies of merely 17%. In addition, these yields are obtained at low <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>only [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. On the other hand, based on thermodynamic aspects, thermophilic bacteria and archaea may produce up to the theoretical maximum of 4 mol H<sub>2</sub>/mol hexose [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. In general, the low H<sub>2 </sub>yields obtained in practice by different organisms, in addition to the requirement for low <italic>P</italic><sub>H2</sub>, are major obstacles that need to be overcome before biohydrogen production can be industrially feasible [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>].</p><p><italic>Caldicellulosiruptor saccharolyticus </italic>is an extreme thermophilic bacterium that can produce high H<sub>2 </sub>yields [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>], and at the same time is relatively insensitive to high <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. This organism has recently gained increased interest due to its ability to produce thermostable cellulolytic and xylanolytic enzymes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>], to grow on complex lignocellulosic carbon sources [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>], and to co-metabolize a wide spectrum of monosaccharides including both pentose and hexose sugars [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. Although <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>possesses these desirable traits and several research articles have been recently published on this heterotrophic strict anaerobe, it has not yet been the subject of a review article. Herein, the physiological properties of <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>will be analyzed to unravel the characteristics required for a superior H<sub>2 </sub>cell factory. To further underline current insights in this topic, the physiology of <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>will be compared with that of other H<sub>2</sub>-producing microorganisms.</p></sec><sec><title>2. Characteristics and natural habitat of <italic>C. saccharolyticus</italic></title><p><italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>is a strictly anaerobic, extreme-thermophilic, Gram-positive bacterium that belongs to the Clostridia class. There are to date 13 characterized species in the genus <italic>Caldicellulosiruptor</italic>, of which <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>is described best, including its whole-genome sequence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. <italic>C. bescii</italic>, formerly known as <italic>Anaerocellum thermophilum</italic>, is the other species in the genus with its genome also fully sequenced [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>was isolated from a piece of wood in a hot spring in the Rotorua-Taupo thermal area in New Zealand, of which the waters have neutral pH, and are low in sulphate, salt content and free sugars [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. Instead, The majority of the sugars present in this environment, such as glucose and xylose, are contained in complex (hemi)cellulosic polymers, which are difficult to access.</p><p><italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>is well adapted to the selective pressure of this habitat through the production of various hydrolyzing enzymes, possession of a wide range of high-affinity transport systems, and absence of glucose-based catabolite repression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>], which are all attractive properties for using the organism for industrial purposes. However, being sensitive to high osmotic pressures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>] is one of the undesirable consequences of adaptation to such environment. Interestingly, <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>is non-motile and non-sporulating [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>], although it possesses a complete set of genes for flagella biosynthesis and several genes required for sporulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>], signifying a historical genetic record of characteristics that could have been required in past habitats.</p></sec><sec><title>3. Genome analysis and carbohydrate utilisation by <italic>C. saccharolyticus</italic></title><p>The genome of <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>has been sequenced and a microarray-based protocol for genome-wide transcriptome analysis has been developed, which is a major convenience for studying and understanding its physiology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>has a relatively small genome of 2,970 kb and 2,760 protein-coding open reading frames (ORFs). From the genome-curation project, several new insights were gained such as the unusually high number of transposons and transposable derivatives <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>possesses, as compared with other organisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. Since transposition increases the chance of genetic alterations, a large number of transposons can enhance the adaptability of this organism and may widen the spectrum of environmental conditions it can grow in, which is beneficial from an industrial point of view. On the other hand, this may also have negative repercussions since it can jeopardize stable fermentation processes. How to balance both impacts in practice needs to be further investigated.</p><p>A general favourable property of members of the Clostridia class is their ability to degrade complex polymers such as cellulosic and lignocellulosic materials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]. Based on growth analysis, <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>can metabolize various carbon sources ranging from monomers, such as xylose, arabinose, glucose, fructose and galactose to &#x003b1;- and &#x003b2;-linked di- and polysaccharides, such as maltose, lactose, sucrose, starch, pullulan, threhalose, xylan and cellulose [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>can also grow and produce H<sub>2 </sub>from complex lignocellulosic materials, both pre-treated, such as Miscanthus hydrolysate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>], sugar beet juice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>] and paper sludge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>], and untreated, such as wheat straw [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>], pine wood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>] and bagasse [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]. The fermentation of these raw materials by <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>has yielded H<sub>2</sub>, CO<sub>2 </sub>and acetate as the main metabolic end products [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>], with a maximum H<sub>2 </sub>yield per consumed hexose of 3.0-3.8 mol/mol [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]. Interestingly, cultivations on Miscanthus hydrolysate were accompanied by complete depletion of oligosaccharides and simultaneous oligosaccharide and monosaccharide consumption [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>degrades complex polymers by producing several cellulolytic and xylanolytic enzymes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. Properties of the cellulase and hemicellulase enzymes of this organism as well as their gene structures have been extensively studied [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. In contrast to cellulolytic clostridia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>], <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>does not contain a cellulosome complex. <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>is unusual with respect to its possession of a multifunctional, multi-domain organisation for the majority of its &#x003b2;-glucanases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. The majority of the xylanases in <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>are clustered in a large gene cluster, and another cluster of genes involved in xylose metabolism is in close proximity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. Detailed information on glycoside hydrolases and other carbohydrate active enzymes encoded by <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>genome can be retrieved from the Carbohydrate Active Enzymes database (CAZy; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cazy.org/">http://www.cazy.org/</ext-link>; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]).</p><p>The manual curation of the genome sequence of <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>indicated that it possesses an unusually high number of ATP-binding cassette (ABC) transporter genes (i.e., at least 177 ABC transporter genes) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]; many of which are responsible for the transport of monomeric and dimeric sugars. <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>has only one sugar phosphotransferase system (PTS), which is believed to be used for fructose transport [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. When <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>was cultivated on a mixture of monosaccharides, they were consumed simultaneously but at different rates, i.e., fructose &#x0003e; arabinose &#x0003e; xylose &#x0003e; mannose &#x0003e; glucose &#x0003e; galactose. Unlike the case with disaccharides, the ABC transporters were not substrate specific for these monosaccharides. Instead, the affinity for the different sugars varied, with a clear preference for pentose sugars. Overall, the genome and transcription analyses revealed that <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>is well equipped for utilizing complex carbohydrates, such as starch and lignocellulosic polysaccharides [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>4. Hydrogen yields</title><p>For cost-efficient biohydrogen production, it is critical to achieve high substrate-conversion efficiencies due to the central cost of the raw material and the need to reduce the chemical oxygen demand (COD) in the waste stream [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Strategies to improve the overall process yield include the application of hybrid two-step systems, consisting of a dark fermentation step combined with either a light fermentation step [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>], or a methanogenesis step [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>]. In this way, the products of the first fermentation process, consisting mainly of volatile fatty acids, can be converted in the second step to either H<sub>2 </sub>and CO<sub>2 </sub>or CH<sub>4 </sub>and CO<sub>2</sub>, respectively. The pros and cons of these two strategies were evaluated in a recent review [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>] and will not be treated herein. Instead, we will focus on H<sub>2 </sub>yields of the dark fermentation step.</p><sec><title>4.1 Metabolic pathways for hydrogen production</title><p>During fermentation, H<sub>2 </sub>is produced by anaerobic heterotrophs as a means to reoxidize their reducing equivalents. The maximum obtainable yield in a dark fermentation process is 4 moles H<sub>2 </sub>per mol of hexose, the so-called Thauer limit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. However, many H<sub>2 </sub>yields reported in literature are less than 50% of the Thauer limit (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Effect of growth temperature on H2 yield.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Organism</th><th align="center">Opt T &#x000b0;C</th><th align="center">Cultivation</th><th align="center">Substrate</th><th align="center">Maximum yield</th><th align="center">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><bold>Mesophiles </bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Escherichia coli </italic>SR15</td><td align="center">37</td><td align="center">Fed-batch</td><td align="center">Glucose</td><td align="center">1.82</td><td align="center">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B85">85</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Enterobacter aerogenes</italic></td><td align="center">40</td><td align="center">Batch</td><td align="center">Glucose</td><td align="center">1.0</td><td align="center">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B99">99</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Enterobacter cloacae</italic></td><td align="center">37</td><td align="center">Packed bed</td><td align="center">Starch</td><td align="center">1.4</td><td align="center">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B100">100</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Clostridium butyricum</italic></td><td align="center">30</td><td align="center">continuous</td><td align="center">Glucose</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B101">101</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Clostridium acetobutilicum</italic></td><td align="center">34</td><td align="center">Fed-batch</td><td align="center">Glucose</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B102">102</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Thermophiles</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Clostridium thermocellum</italic></td><td align="center">60</td><td align="center">Continuous</td><td/><td align="center">3.5</td><td align="center">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B103">103</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Extreme thermophiles</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Thermotoga neopolitana</italic></td><td align="center">77</td><td align="center">Batch</td><td align="center">Glucose</td><td align="center">3.9</td><td align="center">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B104">104</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Thermotoga elfii</italic></td><td align="center">65</td><td align="center">Batch</td><td align="center">Glucose</td><td align="center">3.3</td><td align="center">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Caldicellulosiruptor saccharolyticus</italic></td><td align="center">70</td><td align="center">Continuous</td><td align="center">Glucose</td><td align="center">3.6</td><td align="center">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Caldicellulosiruptor owensensis</italic></td><td align="center">70</td><td align="center">Batch</td><td align="center">Glucose</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">66</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Thermoanaerobacter tengcongensis</italic></td><td align="center">75</td><td align="center">Batch</td><td align="center">Glucose</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Thermoanaerobacter pseudoethanolicus</italic></td><td align="center">70</td><td align="center">Continuous</td><td align="center">Xylose</td><td align="center">1.2</td><td align="center">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B105">105</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Hyper thermophiles</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Thermotoga maritima</italic></td><td align="center">80</td><td align="center">Batch</td><td align="center">Glucose</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Pyrococcus furiosus</italic></td><td align="center">100</td><td align="center">Batch</td><td align="center">Glucose</td><td align="center">3.5</td><td align="center">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Thermococcales kodakaraensis</italic></td><td align="center">88</td><td align="center">Continuous</td><td align="center">Starch</td><td align="center">3.3</td><td align="center">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B106">106</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>A selection of mesophilic, thermophilic and extreme thermophilic H<sub>2</sub>-producing strains, showing their optimal growth temperature and H<sub>2 </sub>yields.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The maximum H<sub>2 </sub>yield obtained during sugar oxidation depends primarily on the catabolic pathway employed. <italic>C. saccharolyticus</italic>, with its H<sub>2 </sub>yields close to the Thauer limit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>], employs the Embden-Meyerhof-Parnas (EMP) pathway to oxidize glucose to pyruvate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. The genome sequence and <sup>13</sup>C-NMR analysis revealed a complete gene setup for the EMP pathway and the non-oxidative part of the pentose phosphate pathway (PPP) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>], which enables the organism to convert different sugars into precursor metabolites and energy. No essential genes for the Entner-Doudoroff (ED) pathway have been found [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. Pyruvate can be oxidized further to acetyl-CoA by pyruvate:ferredoxin oxidoreductase (PFOR), with the generation of reduced ferredoxin (Fd<sub>red</sub>). Molecular H<sub>2 </sub>can be obtained from both NADH (two moles of which are generated through the glyceraldehyde phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH)-catalyzed reaction in the EMP pathway) and Fd<sub>red</sub>, thus resulting in a maximum of 4 mol H<sub>2</sub>/mol hexose (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). Several species of heterotrophic clostridia are also potentially able to produce 4 mol H<sub>2</sub>/mol hexose, as judged by their metabolic network (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>), when pyruvate is exclusively oxidized to acetate and CO<sub>2</sub>. In heterotrophic mesophilic clostridia that carry out acetate-type fermentation, NADH generated in the EMP pathway is reoxidized by NADH:Fd oxidoreductase (NFOR) with the generation of Fd<sub>red</sub>, which is also generated through pyruvate oxidation to acetate. The produced Fd<sub>red </sub>(total 8 mol/mol hexose) can subsequently donate electrons to hydrogenases that reduce protons to H<sub>2 </sub>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>].</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Overview of H<sub>2 </sub>generation pathways in different bacteria</bold>. In <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>(A), H<sub>2 </sub>is produced from NADH and Fd<sub>red</sub>, generated in the breakdown of glucose into acetate and CO<sub>2 </sub>via the EMP pathway. The H<sub>2 </sub>generation pathway in several clostridia carrying out acetate-type fermentation (B) is different from that in <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>in that H<sub>2 </sub>is generated solely from Fd<sub>red</sub>. NADH (generated in the EMP pathway) is converted to Fd<sub>red </sub>via NADH:ferredoxin oxidoreductase catalyzed reaction. In Enterobacteria (C), H<sub>2 </sub>is generated from formate, which is produced in the acetate pathway through the PFL-catalyzed reaction.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1475-2859-9-89-1"/></fig><p>On the other hand, enterobacteria are only able to produce maximally 2 moles H<sub>2</sub>/mol hexose, since H<sub>2 </sub>is generated via the hydrolysis of formate being produced from glucose through the pyruvate formate lyase-catalyzed pyruvate oxidation (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref>). Interestingly, even the introduction of a synthetic ferredoxin-mediated pyruvate-to-H<sub>2 </sub>pathway in <italic>E. coli </italic>resulted in low H<sub>2 </sub>yields (i.e., ~2 mol/mol hexose) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. Some of the possible reasons why mesophilic bacteria can produce only 2 moles H<sub>2</sub>/mol hexose, despite being equipped with the relevant metabolic pathways, are revealed in the following sections.</p></sec><sec><title>4.2 Thermodynamic aspects</title><p>One of the reasons to which the low H<sub>2 </sub>yields observed in mesophilic cultures have been attributed is the thermodynamically unfavourable NADH-dependent H<sub>2</sub>-evolving reaction at <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>&#x0003e; 0.039 kPa and at standard conditions (1 M concentration of the reactants, 25&#x000b0;C, pH 7) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. This is because H<sub>2 </sub>has a lower formal potential than NADH, hence for the reduction of protons by NADH to occur spontaneously, the <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>has to be low. However, these conditions are often not encountered even when the reactor is sparged with an inert gas at a high flow rate (i.e., 400 mL/min), because the H<sub>2 </sub>concentration in the liquid will exceed the critical <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>a 1000-fold [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]. Therefore, in addition to H<sub>2</sub>, mesophilic anaerobes normally form other reduced compounds, such as acetone, butanol, ethanol, and lactate, resulting in a H<sub>2 </sub>yield that usually does not exceed 2 mol/mol hexose (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). A strategy to overcome this problem is to use thermophilic hydrogen producers instead, hence this works a decrease in the Gibbs free energy change of the H<sub>2</sub>-generation reaction in hand (&#x00394;<italic>G'</italic>; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]):</p><p><disp-formula id="bmcM1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1" name="1475-2859-9-89-i1" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mo>'</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>H2</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>where <italic>&#x02206; G</italic><sup>0<italic>' </italic></sup>is the Gibbs free energy at standard conditions (kJ/mol), <italic>R </italic>is the gas constant (kJ/mol&#x000b7;K) and <italic>T </italic>the absolute temperature (K).</p><p>In general, extreme thermophiles reach higher H<sub>2 </sub>yields than mesophiles (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>], and also at higher temperatures the critical <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>is higher. For instance, at a temperature of 70&#x002da;C the critical <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>is 0.173 kPa. However, this value is still well below 60 kPa, at which in practice <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>is still capable of producing 3.6-4.0 moles H<sub>2</sub>/mol glucose [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>].</p><p>To understand this controversy, it is to be noticed that temperature is not the only factor influencing H<sub>2 </sub>generation. The &#x00394;<italic>G</italic><italic>' </italic>of the H<sub>2</sub>-producing process is also a function of the type of cofactor involved and the ratio of reduced to oxidized cofactors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]. Each cofactor has a different formal potential, i.e., the <italic>E</italic><sup>0<italic>' </italic></sup>for Fd<sub>red</sub>/Fd<sub>ox </sub>&#x0003c; NADPH/NADP &#x0003c; NADH/NAD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>], and unless the cofactor specificity of the involved hydrogenase is known, it is not possible to determine the thermodynamics of the system. <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>possesses two distinct hydrogenases, i.e., one NADH-dependent Fe-only hydrogenase (Csac_1860-1864) and one Fd<sub>red</sub>-dependent, membrane-associated NiFe hydrogenase (Csac_1540-1545) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. Given that the formal potential of Fd<sub>red/</sub>Fd<sub>ox </sub>(<italic>E</italic><sup>0' </sup>approx. -400 mV) is close to that of H<sub>2 </sub>(<italic>E</italic><sup>0'</sup><sub>H2</sub>: -414 mV) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>], the Fd-dependent hydrogenase reaction is energetically favourable up to a <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>of 39 kPa at standard conditions. However, this calculation is based on an approximation since the actual midpoint redox potential of Fd depends on the strain and the temperature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. The actual midpoint redox potential for Fd at 70&#x000ba;C in <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>is not known, but should be in the same order of magnitude as found in other related thermophilic bacteria. From the thermodynamic estimation, it is obvious that it is primarily the NADH-dependent Fe-only hydrogenase that is inhibited by elevated <italic>P</italic><sub>H2</sub>. Consistently, the NADH-dependent Fe-only hydrogenase in <italic>Thermoanaerobacter tengcongensis </italic>was downregulated at high <italic>P</italic><sub>H2</sub>, while the Fd-dependent hydrogenase was constitutively expressed, independently of the <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>].</p><p>Recently, Schut and Adams [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>] characterized a novel type of Fe-only hydrogenase in <italic>Thermotoga maritima </italic>(TM1424-TM1426) that uses NADH and Fd<sub>red </sub>simultaneously. This novel bifurcating hydrogenase could therefore catalyze the unfavourable oxidation of NADH to H<sub>2 </sub>by using the exothermic oxidation of ferredoxin as a driving force. Interestingly, the Fe-only hydrogenase genes in <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>(Csac_1860, 1863-1864) show &#x02265; 50% sequence similarities to the bifurcating hydrogenase genes in <italic>Tm. maritima </italic>(TM1424-TM1426), but it remains to be investigated whether this hydrogenase in <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>possesses a bifurcating function. In fact, many of the thermophiles listed in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> and several mesophilic clostridia possess a Fe-only hydrogenase-encoding genes with sequence similarity to TM1424-TM1426 in <italic>Tm. maritima </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]. This observation could give a plausible explanation to the ability of these thermophiles to produce high H<sub>2 </sub>yields in well-sparged bioreactors.</p><p>The ratio of reduced to oxidized cofactors has also a significant impact on the thermodynamics of the system (Eq. 1), which was confirmed experimentally by Velt et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]. In <italic>C. saccharolyticus</italic>, the NADH/NAD ratio changed six folds during growth-phase transition in batch cultures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>], and consequently the value of the critical <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>for hydrogen production will also vary with the growth state of the organism. Similar observations were reported for <italic>Clostridium cellulolyticum </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>], <italic>Cl. butyricum </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>] and <italic>Cl. acetobutylicum </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>]. Therefore, based on the reasoning above, the thermodynamic constraint might not be an absolute parameter for determining the critical <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>for hydrogen production.</p><p>However, the generally higher H<sub>2 </sub>yields obtained by thermophilic organisms still implies that temperature has a significant impact. An intriguing question that arises is why these thermophiles have evolved for optimized H<sub>2 </sub>production. Resolving this phenomenon would aid in designing highly efficient H<sub>2 </sub>cell factories.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>5. Effect of <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>versus dissolved H<sub>2 </sub>concentration</title><p>As discussed above, due to gaps in the knowledge on the redox system in <italic>C. saccharolyticus</italic>, the thermodynamic constraint cannot be used to estimate its tolerance to H<sub>2</sub>. For practical reasons, the <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>in the gas phase is generally used as a measure for H<sub>2 </sub>tolerance. The critical value of <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>(10-20 kPa) as found for <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>is often quoted in the literature, and is defined as the partial pressure of H<sub>2 </sub>at which lactate formation, an alternative way for reoxidizing NADH, is initiated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. This critical <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>was determined in batch cultures of <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>on sucrose using a closed bioreactor without sparging. However, in a similar experimental setup, but with xylose as the substrate, the critical <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>was up to 60 kPa, upon which the metabolism shifted to lactate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. A possible explanation for the observed discrepancy can be based on the difference in the organism's metabolic activity on the two substrates, i.e., the volumetric H<sub>2 </sub>productivity is lower on xylose than on sucrose which results in different concentrations of dissolved H<sub>2 </sub>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. The variation in the observed critical <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>values can also be a consequence of a different distribution pattern of catabolic and anabolic fluxes on the two substrates, leading to different metabolite levels that modulate lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. In that sense, the critical <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>has no strict value, but will depend on the organism, the substrate and probably other environmental factors of the fermentation process. To make it more complicated, in batch cultures on glucose (5 g/L), lactate formation is triggered at the transition to the stationary phase, even though the <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>was low (6.3 kPa) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. Therefore, there are obviously other factors that initiate lactate formation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>], making its use as a proper criterion for defining the critical <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>questionable. Despite lactate being formed, growth still continues, but rather in a linear than an exponential fashion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. In addition, in continuous cultures of <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>on glucose, growth and H<sub>2 </sub>production were still observed at a <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>of 67 kPa at a low dilution rate (0.05 h<sup>-1</sup>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>].</p><p>Kraemer et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>] could not find any coherent correlation between the sparging gas flow rate and H<sub>2 </sub>yield under different fermentation conditions. Due to this ambiguity, one may wonder whether <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>is an appropriate parameter for inferring the critical H<sub>2 </sub>concentration for growth and hydrogen production. Indeed, Pauss et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>] demonstrated in various bioreactor systems that the dissolved H<sub>2 </sub>easily supersaturates the liquid phase and its concentration is far from equilibrium with the gas phase. This can be attributed to the low solubility of H<sub>2 </sub>in water and that H<sub>2 </sub>production takes place in the liquid phase. The dissolved H<sub>2 </sub>concentration is a function of H<sub>2 </sub>productivity and the mass transfer rate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>], where the latter is a function of gas sparging rate and the stirring rate. A study with <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>in a pH and temperature controlled stirred tank reactor confirmed that the dissolved H2 concentration is a more indicative parameter for inhibition of H<sub>2 </sub>production [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. The supersaturation of H<sub>2 </sub>in the liquid enacts a decline in H<sub>2 </sub>productivity via a metabolic shift to lactate, which may be a mechanism to steer away from exceeding the critical dissolved H<sub>2 </sub>concentration at which growth is inhibited [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. To maintain a high productivity the dissolved H<sub>2 </sub>concentration should be kept low through increasing the mass transfer rate in the reactor, e.g. by using an appropriate sparging gas and/or proper reactor design.</p><p>Nonetheless, since data on dissolved H<sub>2 </sub>concentrations are scarce in the literature and <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>is usually the determined parameter, the <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>will continue to be used for comparisons in this review.</p><sec><title>5.1 Hydrogen tolerance and sulphur reduction</title><p>Based on thermodynamics, the heterotrophic archaeon <italic>Pyrococcus furiosus</italic>, with its growth optimum near 100&#x000b0;C [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>], should reach a higher H<sub>2 </sub>yield at higher <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>than that obtained with <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. This organism also has an unusual advantage in that its GAPDH counterpart, glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate: ferredoxin oxidoreductase (GAPOR), generates Fd<sub>red </sub>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>], which has an exceptionally low formal potential (<italic>E'</italic><sub>Fd,100&#x000b0;C </sub>= -600 mV; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]). Therefore, based only on thermodynamic constraints (Eq. 1; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]), <italic>P. furiosus </italic>should be the least H<sub>2</sub>-inhibited anaerobe listed in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. Yet, it produces only 2-3 moles H<sub>2</sub>/mol hexose, it is highly sensitive to an increase in <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>], and, when present, it prefers to reduce S<sup>0 </sup>instead of protons. In nature, low-<italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>environments are usually achievable for H<sub>2 </sub>producers living in symbiosis with hydrogenotrophic methanogens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>].</p><p>This preference for S<sup>0 </sup>can be explained by examining the physiological properties of its hydrogenases, of which <italic>P. furiosus </italic>possesses three distinct sets. It has two cytosolic NiFe-hydrogenases, which can reduce either protons to H<sub>2 </sub>or polysulphide to H<sub>2</sub>S, using NADPH as an electron donor. It also has a membrane-bound NiFe-hydrogenase, which can reduce protons to H<sub>2 </sub>using Fd<sub>red </sub>as an electron donor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>], with the unique capability of generating a proton motive force via proton translocation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>]. Moreover, it has a NiFe-containing hydrogenase complex [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>], but its physiological role is partly unknown. As a third set, the organism possesses a ferredoxin:NADP oxidoreductase (or sulphide dehydrogenase) that regulates product formation depending on the <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>]. In other words, with increasing <italic>P</italic><sub>H2</sub>, this enzyme becomes more active and decreases H<sub>2 </sub>production by transferring electrons from Fd<sub>red </sub>to either polysulphide or NADP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>]. NADPH can then be used to reduce pyruvate to alanine, catalyzed by an NADPH-dependent glutamate dehydrogenase and alanine aminotransferase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>].</p><p>S<sup>0 </sup>reduction by <italic>Thermoanaerobacter tengcongensis </italic>enhances growth, and in its absence the organism is highly sensitive to H<sub>2 </sub>and growth is strongly inhibited at <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>above 10 kPa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. There are, however, <italic>Thermoanaerobacter </italic>species that are H<sub>2</sub>-tolerant, such as the ethanol-adapted <italic>T. thermosulfurigenes </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>]. This adapted strain is able to maintain growth at 1 atm H<sub>2 </sub>by redirecting its metabolism to ethanol, but its H<sub>2 </sub>yield is not higher than 50% of the Thauer limit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>].</p><p>Members of the genus <italic>Thermotoga</italic>, which are isolated from both shallow and deep sea hydrothermal vents rich in S<sup>0 </sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>], are normally able to reduce either S<sup>0 </sup>or thiosulphate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>]. The members of this genus display varying degrees of sensitivity to H<sub>2</sub>, but H<sub>2 </sub>inhibition can be generally relieved by the addition of S<sup>0</sup>, most likely as the result of a "detoxification" reaction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>]. For instance, the <italic>Thermotoga </italic>sp. strains FjSS3.B1 and FjSS.B1 are both highly sensitive to H<sub>2 </sub>and the addition of S<sup>0 </sup>can re-establish their growth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>]. Although not generally required for its growth, <italic>Tm. maritima </italic>is able to reduce S<sup>0</sup>, but does not respire it, decreasing its H<sub>2 </sub>yield by 40% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>]. In a H<sub>2</sub>-pressurized reactor (H<sub>2</sub>/CO<sub>2</sub>, 80/20%; 300 kPa), however, growth of <italic>Tm. maritima </italic>cells was not observed unless S<sup>0 </sup>was added [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>]. Johnson et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>] demonstrated that <italic>Tm. maritima </italic>was strongly inhibited by H<sub>2</sub>, which triggers the cells to enter stationary phase. Consistently, Schr&#x000f6;der et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">64</xref>], demonstrated that <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>levels above 2.3 kPa might be inhibitory to growth of <italic>Tm. maritima</italic>. However, since the organism was cultivated under uncontrolled conditions, other effects, such as the growth-associated drop in pH, might have contributed to growth inhibition. Although <italic>Marinitoga </italic>is closely related to <italic>Thermotoga</italic>, members of this genus can generally tolerate more H<sub>2 </sub>than <italic>Thermotoga </italic>species. For instance, <italic>M. hydrogenotolerans </italic>can grow at 1 atm H<sub>2 </sub>without any reduction in biomass yield, but then ethanol is formed under these conditions, which drains the electrons required for H<sub>2 </sub>production. In addition, in the presence of S<sup>0</sup>, H<sub>2 </sub>is not formed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">65</xref>].</p><p>In contrast, members of the genus <italic>Caldicellulosiruptor </italic>are generally unable to reduce S<sup>0 </sup>or thiosulphate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>]. Moreover, both <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>and <italic>C. owensensis </italic>are capable of growing and producing H<sub>2 </sub>at <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>levels up to 67 and 44 kPa, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">66</xref>]. Similarly, growth of C. <italic>kristjanssonii </italic>was not inhibited at <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>levels up to50 kPa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67">67</xref>].</p><p>The information gathered from the literature so far, in addition to our own work, reveals that S<sup>0</sup>-reducing thermophiles are generally more sensitive to H<sub>2 </sub>than thermophiles that are unable to use S<sup>0 </sup>as an electron acceptor. This conclusion supports the previously proposed correlation between the ability to reduce S<sup>0 </sup>and the sensitivity to H<sub>2 </sub>inhibition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>]. Due to inconsistencies in the experimental design for the different microorganisms studied and the lack of data on dissolved H<sub>2 </sub>concentrations, one should be aware that it is difficult to quantify H<sub>2 </sub>tolerance. In conclusion, based on this knowledge, it can be suggested to select for non-S<sup>0</sup>-reducing H<sub>2</sub>-producing candidates and future attempts to isolate promising H<sub>2 </sub>producers should be targeting S<sup>0</sup>-poor environments.</p></sec><sec><title>5.2 H<sub>2 </sub>removal from the liquid</title><p>To obtain higher H<sub>2 </sub>yields and productivities, high dissolved H<sub>2 </sub>concentrations should be avoided [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>]. Therefore, methods to increase the mass transfer rate of H<sub>2 </sub>from the liquid to the gas phase should be employed. Several studies have been dedicated to develop different ways for efficient removal of H<sub>2 </sub>from the liquid phase (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Comparison of different sparging conditions</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center">Sparging gas</th><th align="center">Separation</th><th align="left">Benefits</th><th align="left">Drawbacks</th><th align="center">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">N<sub>2</sub></td><td align="center">Difficult</td><td align="left">Not inhibitory</td><td align="left">Difficult to separate from H<sub>2 </sub>Expensive</td><td align="center">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="center">CO<sub>2</sub></td><td align="center">Easy</td><td align="left">Easily separated Produced in the process</td><td align="left">Increases osmolarity Inhibits H<sub>2 </sub>productivity</td><td align="center">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="center">CH<sub>4</sub></td><td align="center">Easy</td><td align="left">Easily separated Produced in a hybrid biohydrogen/biogas process</td><td align="left">No results available for <italic>C. saccharolyticus</italic></td><td align="center">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Under-pressure</td><td align="center">Easy</td><td align="left">Not inhibitory <break/>No dilution of the gas<break/>Cheap separation</td><td align="left">Expensive at large scale<break/>Risk of contamination</td><td align="center">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">68</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="center">No sparging</td><td align="center">Easy</td><td align="left">No dilution of the gas<break/>Cheap separation</td><td align="left">Inhibits H<sub>2 </sub>productivity <break/>Inhibits H<sub>2 </sub>yield</td><td align="center">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Currently, N<sub>2 </sub>is commonly used as a sparging gas for lab-scale H<sub>2 </sub>production. However, applying this method at an industrial scale is not cost-effective since N<sub>2 </sub>is inert, and thus difficult to remove from the effluent gas stream [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Instead, CO<sub>2 </sub>could be an appropriate alternative since it can be more readily separated from H<sub>2 </sub>and, as a convenience, it is a product of the fermentation process itself [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Nevertheless, being chemically non inert, CO<sub>2 </sub>can influence the metabolism of some microorganisms as well as the composition of the culture medium, and hence may not be viewed as an adequate universal sparging gas. In <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>cultures, CO<sub>2 </sub>was already shown to negatively influence growth and H<sub>2 </sub>production rate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. In that study, higher partial pressures of CO<sub>2 </sub>(<italic>P</italic><sub>CO2</sub>) were found to increase the concentration of dissolved CO<sub>2</sub>, which is hydrolyzed to bicarbonate and protons. This requires the addition of larger amounts of a caustic agent to compensate for the decrease in pH, contributing to an increased osmotic pressure, which inhibits growth in <italic>C. saccharolyticus</italic>, and a higher environmental burden [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. Methane is another interesting alternative sparging gas that was previously shown to improve the H<sub>2 </sub>yield of a mesophilic consortium by 88% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. However, the effect of this gas on H<sub>2 </sub>production by <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>has not been investigated yet.</p><p>Other strategies, such as applying reduced pressure to remove H<sub>2 </sub>and CO<sub>2 </sub>from the headspace, have been shown to efficiently increase H<sub>2 </sub>yields in <italic>Enterobacter cloacae </italic>at lab scale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">68</xref>]. However, on an industrial scale, this strategy might not be economically feasible due to high energy cost and increased contamination risk. Instead, two other alternative approaches may be pursued: i) improvement of reactor design to decrease the levels of dissolved H<sub>2 </sub>and CO<sub>2</sub>, and ii) metabolic engineering of the organism to enable it to either produce higher H<sub>2 </sub>yields at high <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>or to withstand higher osmotic pressures.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>6. Sugar transport and energy conservation</title><p>Based on its genome sequence and transcriptome analysis, <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>appears to rely primarily on ABC transporters for sugar uptake [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. Bacterial and archaeal ABC transporters consist of five subunits, i.e., a sugar-binding protein, two transmembrane domains and two nucleotide-binding domains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">69</xref>]. A common characteristic of the sugar binding protein is its ability to capture the sugar outside the cell via a cap-lock mechanism, which determines the high affinity of the transporter for the substrate. Despite the large number of ABC transporters in <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>], none of them have been characterized so far. However, based on transcriptional analysis, it has been concluded that, in <italic>C. saccharolyticus</italic>, the same transporter might translocate different sugars with varying affinities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>].</p><p>From a physiological perspective, ABC transporters have the disadvantage of relatively high energy demand, compared with the phosphoenol pyruvate (PEP)-dependent phosphotransferase system (PTS) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">70</xref>]. In the latter system, one mole of the high-energy compound PEP is required for both sugar transport and subsequent phosphorylation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">70</xref>], whereas two moles of ATP are required for the same steps using an ABC transporter. The fuelling of these energy demanding, high-affinity transport systems in a strict anaerobe such as <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>requires an efficient energy-conserving metabolism. It can be hypothesized that one of these energy-conserving strategies is the oxidation of glucose to acetate and CO<sub>2</sub>, which results in two extra moles of ATP per mole of hexose on top of the usual ATP yield of 2 mol/mol hexose in the EMP pathway. Thus, with the conversion of glucose to two moles of acetate, maximally four moles of ATP can be acquired, with the net yield being only three moles if an ABC transporter is involved (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). This means that with acetate as the end product, the desired H<sub>2 </sub>production becomes advantageous for the microorganism since it serves as an electron sink in the re-oxidation of the reduced cofactors Fd<sub>red </sub>and NADH generated in the breakdown of sugars.</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Theoretical ATP yield (YATP/S) (mol/mol) of anaerobic glucose oxidation with different transport systems and fermentation products.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center">Transport</th><th align="center" colspan="6">Fermentation product</th></tr><tr><th/><th align="center">acetate</th><th align="center">lactate</th><th align="center">ethanol</th><th align="center">butyrate</th><th align="center">butanol</th><th align="center">propionate</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">ABC</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td></tr><tr><td align="center">PTS</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">2</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>To investigate the presented hypothesis further, the genomes of known H<sub>2</sub>-yielding anaerobes were analyzed to evaluate whether they possess PTS- or ABC-type of sugar transport. Indeed, there is a clear correlation between high H<sub>2 </sub>yields and the use of ABC transporters (Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> &#x00026;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>). Organisms that were able to produce high H<sub>2 </sub>yields generally possess mainly ABC-type transporters, whereas low H<sub>2</sub>-yielding bacteria utilize more PTSs for transport. This correlation between H<sub>2 </sub>yields and possession of ABC transporters is more pronounced in thermophiles. For example, the extreme thermophile <italic>Thermoanaerobacter pseudoethanolicus</italic>, which has a PTS for glucose uptake, is unable to produce more than 2 moles H<sub>2</sub>/mol hexose (101), and mainly forms ethanol as a metabolic end product instead of acetate.</p><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>The type of transport system with respect to growth temperature.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Organism</th><th align="center">Opt T &#x000b0;C</th><th align="center">Transporters</th><th align="center">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>Enterobacter aerogenes</italic></td><td align="center">37</td><td align="center">PTS</td><td align="center">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B107">107</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Enterobacter cloacae</italic></td><td align="center">37</td><td align="center">PTS</td><td align="center">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B107">107</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Clostridium butyricum</italic></td><td align="center">30</td><td align="center">PTS</td><td align="center">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Clostridium acetobutylicum</italic></td><td align="center">34</td><td align="center">PTS</td><td align="center">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B108">108</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Clostridium thermocellum</italic></td><td align="center">60</td><td align="center">ABC</td><td align="center">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B109">109</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>C. saccharolyticus</italic></td><td align="center">70</td><td align="center">ABC</td><td align="center">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Thermotoga neopolitana</italic></td><td align="center">77</td><td align="center">ABC</td><td align="center">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B110">110</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Thermoanaerobacter tengcongensis</italic></td><td align="center">75</td><td align="center">ABC</td><td align="center">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Thermoanaerobacter pseudoethanolicus</italic></td><td align="center">70</td><td align="center">PTS</td><td align="center">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Pyrococcus furiosus</italic></td><td align="center">90</td><td align="center">ABC</td><td align="center">This study</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>A selection of mesophilic, thermophilic and extreme thermophilic H<sub>2</sub>-producing strains, showing their optimal growth temperature, H<sub>2 </sub>yields and type of glucose transport. The type of glucose transport assigned to each organism was either retrieved from literature or based on bioinformatic analysis (This study) using the Integrated Microbial Genomes (IMG) database <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://img.jgi.doe.gov/">http://img.jgi.doe.gov/</ext-link></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><sec><title>6.1 PPi as an additional energy carrier</title><p>Another strategy to conserve energy employed by <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>is to utilize inorganic PPi as an additional energy carrier [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">71</xref>]. This strategy is widely applied by anaerobes and other organisms that can acquire only low energy outputs in their metabolism to obtain sufficient ATP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">72</xref>], of which <italic>Tm. maritima </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">73</xref>] and various <italic>Clostridium </italic>species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">72</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">73</xref>] are a few examples that have been studied to some extent.</p><p>The primary sources of PPi are poly-nucleic acid biosynthesis from (deoxy)nucleotide triphosphates and activation of amino acids and fatty acids for protein and lipid synthesis, respectively, which are reactions that operate close to equilibrium. Therefore, subsequent PPi hydrolysis is required for driving these reactions forward [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74">74</xref>]. Moreover, studies on <italic>E. coli </italic>have shown that maintaining low PPi concentrations through effective PPi hydrolysis is required for rapid growth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">75</xref>]. In <italic>E. coli</italic>, as in a majority of other organisms, PPi hydrolysis is catalyzed by a cytosolic inorganic pyrophosphatase (PPase), with the dissipation of the free-energy change of the bound PPi (&#x00394;<italic>G</italic><sup>0'</sup>=-21.8 kJ/mol; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B76">76</xref>]) as heat.</p><p><italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>lacks a cytosolic PPase. Instead, the energy of PPi hydrolysis can be conserved, for instance through: (i) an active membrane-bound PPase employing the free-energy change of the phosphate bond hydrolysis to establish a proton motive force that could be utilized for transport of nutrients or for ATP synthesis; (ii) a PPi-dependent phosphofructokinase (PPi-PFK) in addition to the ATP-dependent one (ATP-PFK); and (iii) a PPi-dependent pyruvate phosphate dikinase (PPdK) in addition to the ADP-dependent pyruvate kinase (PYK; Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">71</xref>].</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Proposed catabolic network in <italic>C. saccharolyticus</italic></bold>. Glucose is transported over the membrane by an ABC transport system (1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>] and oxidized to pyruvate in the EMP pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>], with the possibility that PPi can potentially replace ATP, i.e., PPi-PFK (2) instead of ATP-PFK (3), or ADP, i.e., PPDK (5) instead of PYK (6) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">71</xref>]. NADH generated through the GAPDH-catalyzed reaction (4) and Fd<sub>red </sub>generated from the PFOR-catalyzed reaction (7) can donate electrons for the generation of molecular H<sub>2 </sub>catalyzed by cytosolic NADH-dependent Fe-only hydrogenase and membrane-bound Fd-dependent NiFe-hydrogenase, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. Acetate is formed by the consecutive actions of phosphotransacetylase (PTA; 8) and acetate kinase (AK; 9), with the generation of ATP. Alternative routes for NADH reoxidation are the formation of lactate (LDH; 11), ethanol (ADH; 10) or succinate (12) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. The solid lines represent metabolic routes, whereas the dashed lines represent metabolite activation (+) or inhibition (-) of enzyme activities. PPi generated from anabolic reactions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">71</xref>] is a strong inhibitor of both PYK and LDH activities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">71</xref>].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1475-2859-9-89-2"/></fig><p>Interestingly, there are indications that the PPi-level follows the growth dynamics of <italic>C. saccharolyticus</italic>. When the cells were growing exponentially at the maximum growth rate, the PPi levels were relatively high (4 &#x000b1; 2 mM), and when the growth rate decreased, the PPi levels declined concordantly. The dynamics in PPi levels were shown to be associated with the low cytosolic PPase activity in <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">71</xref>]. Consistently, the PPi levels followed the same growth-dependent trend in <italic>Moorella thermoacetica </italic>and <italic>Cl. pasteurianum</italic>, both of which also lack a cytosolic PPase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B76">76</xref>]. In contrast, in <italic>E. coli </italic>possessing elevated cytosolic PPase activity (0.54 U/mg cdw), the PPi levels were low (0.3 mM) and did not fluctuate during growth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B76">76</xref>].</p><p>Unlike PPi, the ATP levels in <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>were very low (0.43 &#x000b1; 0.07 mM) during the exponential growth phase, but increased 2 folds at the beginning of the stationary phase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">71</xref>]. Interestingly, the ADP concentration was higher than that of ATP during both phases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">71</xref>], which is generally considered to be a sign of starvation. Similar low ATP/ADP ratios were observed in <italic>Cl. acetobutylicum </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B77">77</xref>]. Nevertheless, <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>grew exponentially, suggesting that it relies on other energy carriers, such as PPi, that may contribute to its energy charge in addition to ATP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">71</xref>].</p><p>The use of PPi as an additional energy carrier also introduces greater metabolic flexibility. In addition, it creates a stronger link between anabolism and catabolism, i.e., the net ATP generated in catabolic pathways is used as an energy input in biosynthetic pathways, which generates PPi that can participate in driving catabolism and generating ATP (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). In this cycle, both ATP and PPi may be key regulators of catabolic and anabolic fluxes.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Schematic representation of the suggested circulation of energy carriers in catabolism and anabolism in <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>during exponential growth (A), and non-growth (B), and its influence on metabolite formation</bold>. During exponential growth, there is a high energy demand in the cells. The formation of acetate allows maximum ATP gain and high levels of PPi secure economical use of ATP, including the inhibition of LDH activity and prevention of lactate formation. During non-growth, the ATP demands in the cells are reduced and LDH activity is restored due to the absence of PPi.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1475-2859-9-89-3"/></fig></sec><sec><title>6.2 Enzyme regulation</title><p>Regulation of the classical glycolysis and the flux distribution at the pyruvate node is a very complex and highly tuned process, since it is the principal provider of energy carriers and redox equivalents that need to be precisely balanced under all growth conditions. Regulation takes place at metabolite level as well as at enzyme and gene expression levels. Enzyme activities normally are regulated via direct mass action law (concentrations of substrates or effectors) or via allosteric inhibition or activation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B78">78</xref>]. To maintain high growth rate conditions, cells of <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>should obtain optimal energy gain from the substrate to fuel both anabolism and sugar transport, and thus lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) and alcohol dehydrogenase (ADH) should be kept inactive (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Indeed, a recent batch-fermentation study has shown that during exponential growth, H<sub>2</sub>, CO<sub>2 </sub>and acetate are the only fermentation products in <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. In this growth phase, neither ethanol nor lactate was formed, although both LDH and ADH activities were detected in crude cell extracts at high levels. However, as the growth rate decreased during transition to the stationary phase, the metabolism was partly directed towards lactate formation. Similar growth phase-related metabolic shifts have been observed in <italic>Cl. cellulolyticum </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>]. Studying the <italic>in vitro </italic>kinetics of LDH activity in <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>confirmed the observations of the batch experiments. It revealed that LDH activity in <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>is strongly regulated by the levels of the energy carriers PPi and ATP, in addition to the NADH/NAD ratio (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. When the cells are growing at the maximum specific growth rate, PPi levels are high and ATP levels are low, keeping LDH inactive and its affinity for NADH low. It further assures that the catabolic flux is directed to acetate and H<sub>2 </sub>(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). However, as soon as the anabolic activity declines, the PPi/ATP ratio drops by an order of magnitude [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">71</xref>], which results in an increase in LDH activity as well as its affinity for NADH and hence lactate starts being formed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>].</p><p>Due to the strong control of <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>LDH activity at enzyme level, lactate is formed only in special cases, i.e., at elevated NADH/NAD ratios and at higher ATP levels. High NADH/NAD ratios also lead to inhibition of GAPDH activity and consequently the glycolytic flux [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. Since LDH activity secures the continuation of the glycolytic flux, through diminishing the NADH/NAD ratio, the enzyme can be considered essential for balanced growth in <italic>C. saccharolyticus</italic>. It thus might be questioned whether deleting the <italic>ldh </italic>gene would improve H<sub>2 </sub>yields during sugar fermentation. It might be a better approach to control lactate production through maintaining process conditions that promote exponential growth to keep high cellular PPi levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. It is worth noting that deletion of the <italic>ldh </italic>gene in <italic>E. coli </italic>only slightly increased H<sub>2 </sub>yield and productivities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">79</xref>].</p><p>Ethanol is another reduced end product that is formed during growth of <italic>C. saccharolyticus</italic>, albeit in very low quantities (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]). Based on sequence similarities to the characterized ADH in <italic>T. ethanolicus </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">80</xref>], ADH in <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>possesses a NADPH-binding domain instead of a NADH-binding domain (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. This observation is supported by a preliminary kinetic study showing that the affinity of the ADH of <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>for NADPH is higher than for NADH [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>], indicating that ethanol and H<sub>2 </sub>formation do not compete for the same reduced cofactor.</p><p><sup>13</sup>C-NMR analysis of intact cells has also revealed that <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>is capable of reducing either pyruvate or PEP to succinate (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>) in the reductive branch of its incomplete TCA cycle. However, the succinate yield is significantly lower than that of acetate or lactate under regular growth conditions and might only operate under combined elevated <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>and <italic>P</italic><sub>CO2 </sub>levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>].</p><p>Understanding the regulation of the key glycolytic enzyme GAPDH in <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>may also contribute to a better understanding of the organism's ability to tolerate elevated <italic>P</italic><sub>H2</sub>. In general, GAPDH is strongly regulated by the NADH/NAD ratio [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B81">81</xref>], and GAPDH in <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>proved to be no exception [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. However, the enzyme in <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>is more resistant to increased NADH levels than GAPDH in most other related bacteria. The NADH concentration required for 50% inhibition of the enzyme in <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>was 0.03 mM, as compared to 0.01 mM in <italic>T. thermohydrosulfuricus </italic>(formerly known as <italic>Cl. thermohydrosulfuricum</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>] and <italic>Cl. acetobutylicum </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B77">77</xref>]. This observation would in theory have a significant impact on the organism's tolerance to H<sub>2</sub>, i.e., if GAPDH was less inhibited by NADH, higher NADH/NAD ratios could be tolerated in the cell without affecting the glycolytic flux. As discussed above, this would also render the hydrogenase reaction more energetically favourable (Eq. 1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. Consistently, the ethanol-adapted <italic>T. thermohydrosulfuricus </italic>strain possesses a GAPDH that tolerates approximately twice the amount of NADH and is more tolerant to H<sub>2 </sub>than the wild-type strain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>]. Likewise, the NADH/NAD ratio in <italic>Cl. cellulyticum </italic>is significantly higher than in <italic>C. saccharolyticus</italic>, which is possibly due to a more relaxed inhibition of its GAPDH by NADH (50% inhibition at 0.1 mM NADH) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec><title>7. Challenges for optimizing hydrogen production by <italic>C. saccharolyticus</italic></title><p><italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>has several desirable characteristics needed for a H<sub>2 </sub>cell factory, such as its high H<sub>2 </sub>yields on a wide spectrum of carbon sources, its relatively high tolerance to elevated <italic>P</italic><sub>H2</sub>, and its inability to reduce S<sup>0</sup>, which therefore does not interfere with its H<sub>2 </sub>production capabilities. However, the organism also lacks several properties, which should be considered before it can be used industrially.</p><sec><title>7.1 Sensitivity to high osmolalities</title><p>Primarily, the sensitivity of <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>to increased osmotic pressures is a major drawback that should be addressed. The critical concentration of salts and solutes at which the growth of the organism ceases completely was estimated to be 400-425 mM [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. Osmolalities above 0.218 osm/kg H<sub>2</sub>O were found to induce cell lysis in <italic>C. saccharolyticus</italic>, as indicated by increased protein and DNA concentrations in the culture supernatant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. This low osmotolerance imposes limitations on sparging the culture with CO<sub>2 </sub>and on the maximum sugar concentration in the medium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>], with the latter obviously having a negative effect on H<sub>2 </sub>productivity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. On the other hand, the hyperthermophiles <italic>Tm. neapolitana </italic>and <italic>P. furiosus </italic>can grow optimally in the presence of 0.46 M NaCl and 0.5 M NaCl, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">82</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B83">83</xref>]. These salt concentrations correspond to an additional 0.92 and 1 osm/kg H<sub>2</sub>O, respectively, in the culture media, demonstrating that these two hyperthermophiles are better protected against osmotic stress than <italic>C. saccharolyticus</italic>. This higher osmotic tolerance is due to their ability to produce compatible solutes, or osmoprotectants, such as &#x003b2;-mannosylglycerate, di-myo-insitol phosphate and glutamate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">82</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B83">83</xref>]. It remains to be investigated whether <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>is also able to efficiently synthesize similar solutes when exposed to osmotic stress. The low salt concentration in its natural habitat [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>] may have resulted in the loss of any capability to survive in an unfavourable osmotic environment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">82</xref>]. However, the presence of biosynthetic genes for some osmoprotectants, such as proline and glutamate, could open the way for directed evolution to render <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>more osmotolerant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>7.2 Low productivities</title><p>The low cell density of cultures of <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>and other thermophiles, is another major drawback for industrial-scale application. It results in a low volumetric H<sub>2 </sub>productivity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B83">83</xref>], unless dialysis or cell-recycling methods are used to increase the cell mass [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B84">84</xref>]. Especially dialysis was found to increase the cell density of <italic>Pyrococcus furiosus </italic>by an order of magnitude, indicating that the presence of metabolic products prevents the increase in cell densities. In continuous cultures of <italic>C. saccharolyticus</italic>, the volumetric productivity could be enhanced by increasing the dilution rates, but this comes at the expense of the H<sub>2 </sub>yield [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B85">85</xref>]. The decrease in yield could be related to increased dissolved H<sub>2 </sub>concentrations resulting from higher H<sub>2 </sub>productivities[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. This can inhibit the hydrogenase activity and ultimately results in a metabolic shift to lactate. The same trade off between yield and productivity was also observed with other microorganisms. For instance, <italic>E. coli </italic>produces much lower H<sub>2 </sub>yields but its volumetric productivity is almost 100-fold higher than in <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B86">86</xref>]. The cell density is about 200 times higher for <italic>E. coli </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B85">85</xref>] than for <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>], which contributes considerably to the higher volumetric productivity. The specific H<sub>2 </sub>productivity of <italic>E. coli</italic>, however, is low, which could be an undesirable consequence of the higher cell number, i.e., it enhances the H<sub>2 </sub>mass-transfer resistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B85">85</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>7.3 Biofilm formation and reactor design</title><p>Since <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>exhibits a relatively high specific H<sub>2 </sub>productivity, its volumetric production rate can potentially be enhanced through increasing its cell density [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B83">83</xref>] by, for example, inducing biofilm formation. The reactor configuration is an important factor in enhancing biofilm formation. So far, most research on <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>has been carried out in continuously stirred tank reactors (CSTR) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B85">85</xref>], which do not allow for efficient biomass retention. Alternative reactors that enhance biofilm formation include trickling-bed bioreactors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>] and fluidized-bed systems with granules [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B86">86</xref>]. Trickling-bed bioreactors promote biofilm growth by means of packing material with a high surface area within the trickling bed. The liquid passes continuously through the filter, such that it guarantees a good liquid-gas exchange. In the fluidized-bed system, the biofilm is also formed as granules. This reactor system increases the turbulence, thus providing an enhanced mass transfer, which potentially also could decrease the dissolved H<sub>2 </sub>concentration, and hence, improve H<sub>2 </sub>yields. It should be noted that the biofilm mode of growth also offers the surface-attached and matrix-encased bacteria a means of protection against several stressful environmental conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B87">87</xref>], which could benefit an organism like <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>in tolerating higher osmotic pressures. Recently, another <italic>Caldicellulosiruptor </italic>sp., viz. <italic>Caldicellulosiruptor owensensis</italic>, was shown capable of biofilm formation in both trickling-bed and fluidized-bed reactors at 70&#x000b0;C [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B88">88</xref>]. Moreover, the organism retained its ability to grow and produce H<sub>2 </sub>in the fluidized-bed system even in complete absence of gas sparging.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>8. Conclusions</title><p>This review article has focused on <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>as having several desirable characteristics for efficient H<sub>2 </sub>production. This is not only due to the high growth temperature of this organism, but there are strong indications that its metabolic constitution is adapted to efficiently extract energy from carbohydrates, thereby allowing the production of H<sub>2 </sub>at yields close to the Thauer limit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. The energy metabolism of <italic>C. saccharolyticus</italic>, based on maximum ATP production per sugar unit and the use of PPi as an alternative energy carrier, might be correlated with the vast number of ABC transporters it employs. The efficiency of the energy metabolism is further illustrated by the modulation of LDH activity in <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>through the levels of the energy carriers ATP and PPi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]; an active LDH will significantly lower the ATP production flux and thus the growth and H<sub>2 </sub>production rates, in addition to draining the electrons required for H<sub>2 </sub>production.</p><p><italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>can simultaneously co-utilize a wide variety of different sugars [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>] and produces efficient extracellular hydrolytic enzymes, including cellulases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. It has a relatively high tolerance to partial hydrogen pressures that might be related to its inability to reduce S<sup>0</sup>.</p><p>The set of capabilities of <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>described above is the foundation to exploit this organism in a commercial process using various raw materials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B89">89</xref>]. However, for obvious economical reasons the performance of <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>needs to be further improved, i.e., both high H<sub>2 </sub>yields and productivities should be obtained at relatively high <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>].</p><p>Several metabolic engineering strategies can be foreseen to improve H<sub>2 </sub>yields of <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>beyond 3.5 mol/mol hexose, without the need for gas sparging. First, the NADH-dependent GAPDH in <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>could be replaced with an Fd-dependent GAPOR, similar to the one in <italic>P. furiosus </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>] making the corresponding H<sub>2</sub>-generation reaction spontaneous even at elevated <italic>P</italic><sub>H2 </sub>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]. Second, introducing the genes for the oxidative part of the PPP supplemented with an NADPH-dependent hydrogenase could allow the oxidation of one mole of hexose to one mole of acetate and four moles of CO<sub>2 </sub>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B90">90</xref>]. This would in theory yield 8 mol H<sub>2</sub>/mol hexose, but would not help overcome the thermodynamic barrier.</p><p><italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>exhibits a considerably high specific H<sub>2 </sub>production rate compared to other H<sub>2 </sub>producers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B83">83</xref>], but poor volumetric productivities are obtained since its maximum cell densities is in the range of 10<sup>8</sup>-10<sup>9 </sup>cells/mL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Strategies to increase the cell density by at least an order of magnitude would be through inducing biofilm formation and/or increasing the substrate concentration. The latter requires strains with at least 5-fold increased osmotolerance, which might be obtained through evolutionary engineering. It is noteworthy that <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>possesses all the essential genes necessary for biosynthesis of compatible solutes, such as glutamate and proline [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>].</p><p>As a technical approach, oversaturation of H<sub>2 </sub>in the liquid phase should be avoided to stabilize the fermentation process. This can be solved by smart reactor design and process configuration. Different membrane reactors have been developed, which are capable of reducing dissolved H<sub>2 </sub>concentrations and have a positive effect on H<sub>2 </sub>yields [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B91">91</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B94">94</xref>]. Yet, it remains to be investigated how <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>would perform in these reactor systems.</p><p>All in all, it is vital to understand the physiology of H<sub>2 </sub>production, which can be facilitated through applying genetic engineering and state-of-the-art 'omics' tools. However, so far, genetic protocols have been developed only for a few thermophilic hydrogen producers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B95">95</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B98">98</xref>], but not yet for <italic>C. saccharolyticus</italic>. Omics-based technologies are increasingly applied for studying thermophilic H<sub>2 </sub>producers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B99">99</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B100">100</xref>], including <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. Together with genome-wide metabolic models, now being developed for some thermophiles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B101">101</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B102">102</xref>], the systems biology approach can eventually be applied to accelerate our understanding of the physiology of <italic>C. saccharolyticus </italic>and other thermophiles to increase their potential for process applications.</p><p>The insights in the physiology of <italic>C. saccharolyticus</italic>, as covered in this review, should contribute to better strategies for the isolation and/or engineering of future superior H<sub>2 </sub>producers. Creating a superior H<sub>2 </sub>cell factory is a quintessential step towards a sustainable biological H<sub>2 </sub>production.</p></sec><sec><title>9. Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>10. Authors' contributions</title><p>KW conceived of the study, designed and drafted the manuscript. AAZ contributed to the design and content of the review article and helped to draft the manuscript. EWJN helped to draft the manuscript. AAZ and EWJN critically revised and commented the manuscript.</p><p>All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><sec><title>11. Acknowledgements</title><p>AAZ acknowledges support from the Ministry of Higher Education in Egypt. The research on biohydrogen production in our lab is financially supported by the Commission of European Communities, Sixth Framework Program, Priority 6, Sustainable Energy Systems (019825 HYVOLUTION) and the Swedish Energy Agency (Energimyndigheten; 31090-1).</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Claassen</surname><given-names>PAM</given-names></name><name><surname>van Lier</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Contreras</surname><given-names>AML</given-names></name><name><surname>van Niel</surname><given-names>EWJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sijtsma</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Stams</surname><given-names>AJM</given-names></name><name><surname>de Vries</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Weusthuis</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><article-title>Utilisation of biomass for the supply of energy carriers</article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>1999</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>741</fpage><lpage>755</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s002530051586</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>de Vrije</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakker</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Budde</surname><given-names>MAW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mars</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Claassen</surname><given-names>PAM</given-names></name><article-title>Efficient hydrogen production from the lignocellulosic energy crop Miscanthus by the extreme thermophilic bacteria <italic>Caldicellulosiruptor saccharolyticus </italic>and <italic>Thermotoga neapolitana</italic></article-title><source>Biotech Biofuels</source><year>2009</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>12</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1754-6834-2-12</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jen</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lay</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><article-title>Flow-FISH analysis and isolation of clostridial strains in an anaerobic semi-solid bio-hydrogen producing system by hydrogenase gene target</article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2007</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>1126</fpage><lpage>1134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-006-0740-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17277963</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Otsuka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Morimoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Hydrogen production from industrial wastewater by anaerobic microflora in chemostat culture</article-title><source>J Ferment Bioeng</source><year>1996</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>194</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0922-338X(96)85050-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Angelidaki</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><article-title>Hydrogen and methane production from household solid waste in the two-stage fermentation process</article-title><source>Water Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>2230</fpage><lpage>2236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2006.03.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16725172</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hallenbeck</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>Advances in fermentative biohydrogen production: the way forward?</article-title><source>Trends Biotechnol</source><year>2009</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>287</fpage><lpage>297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tibtech.2009.02.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19329204</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kov&#x000e1;cs</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mar&#x000f3;ti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000e1;khely</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>A novel approach for biohydrogen production</article-title><source>Int J Hydrogen Energy</source><year>2006</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1460</fpage><lpage>1468</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijhydene.2006.06.011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Claassen</surname><given-names>PAM</given-names></name><name><surname>de Vrije</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><article-title>Non-thermal production of pure hydrogen from biomass: HYVOLUTION</article-title><source>Int J Hydrogen Energy</source><year>2006</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1416</fpage><lpage>1423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijhydene.2006.06.006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Thauer</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Jungermann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Decker</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>Energy conservation in chemotrophic anaerobic bacteria</article-title><source>Bacteriol Rev</source><year>1977</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">860983</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stams</surname><given-names>AJM</given-names></name><article-title>Metabolic interactions between anaerobic bacteria in methanogenic environments</article-title><source>Antonie Van Leeuwenhoek</source><year>1994</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>294</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00871644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7747937</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>van Groenestijn</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hazewinkel</surname><given-names>JHO</given-names></name><name><surname>Nienoord</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bussmann</surname><given-names>PJT</given-names></name><article-title>Energy aspects of biological hydrogen production in high rate bioreactors operated in the thermophilic temperature range</article-title><source>Int J Hydrogen Energy</source><year>2002</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1141</fpage><lpage>1147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0360-3199(02)00096-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kleerebezem</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>van Loosdrecht</surname><given-names>MCM</given-names></name><article-title>Mixed culture biotechnology for bioenergy production</article-title><source>Curr Opin Biotechnol</source><year>2007</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.copbio.2007.05.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17509864</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Kengen</surname><given-names>SWM</given-names></name><name><surname>Goorissen</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Verhaart</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>van Niel</surname><given-names>EWJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Claassen</surname><given-names>PAM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stams</surname><given-names>AJM</given-names></name><person-group person-group-type="editor">Soetaert W, Vandamme EJ</person-group><article-title>Biological hydrogen production by anaerobic microorganisms</article-title><source>Biofuels</source><year>2009</year><publisher-name>Chichester: John Wiley &#x00026; Sons</publisher-name><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>221</lpage><comment>full_text</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>de Vrije</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mars</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Budde</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Dijkema</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>de Waard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Claassen</surname><given-names>PAM</given-names></name><article-title>Glycolytic pathway and hydrogen yield studies of the extreme thermophile <italic>Caldicellulosiruptor saccharolyticus</italic></article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2007</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>1358</fpage><lpage>1367</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-006-0783-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17216445</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>van Niel</surname><given-names>EWJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Budde</surname><given-names>MAW</given-names></name><name><surname>de Haas</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Wal</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Claassen</surname><given-names>PAM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stams</surname><given-names>AJM</given-names></name><article-title>Distinctive properties of high hydrogen producing extreme thermophiles, <italic>Caldicellulosiruptor saccharolyticus </italic>and <italic>Thermotoga elfii</italic></article-title><source>Int J Hydrogen Energy</source><year>2002</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1391</fpage><lpage>1398</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0360-3199(02)00115-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Willquist</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><source>Physiology of <italic>Caldicellulosiruptor saccharolyticus</italic>: a hydrogen cell factory</source><year>2010</year><publisher-name>PhD thesis Lund University, Applied Microbiology</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gibbs</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Reeves</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrington</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergquist</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><article-title>Multidomain and multifunctional glycosyl hydrolases from the extreme thermophile <italic>Caldicellulosiruptor </italic>isolate Tok7B.1</article-title><source>Curr Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>340</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s002849910066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10706665</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><article-title>Effects of galactose and glucose on the hydrolysis reaction of a thermostable beta-galactosidase from <italic>Caldicellulosiruptor saccharolyticus</italic></article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2009</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>1427</fpage><lpage>1435</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-009-2165-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19662397</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibbs</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergquist</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><article-title>Family 10 and 11 xylanase genes from <italic>Caldicellulosiruptor </italic>sp strain Rt69B.1</article-title><source>Extremophiles</source><year>1999</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s007920050105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10356996</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dwivedi</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibbs</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Saul</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergquist</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><article-title>Cloning, sequencing and overexpression in <italic>Escherichia coli </italic>of a xylanase gene, <italic>xynA </italic>from the thermophilic bacterium Rt8B.4 genus <italic>Caldicellulosiruptor</italic></article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>1996</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s002530050653</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8920183</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bergquist</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibbs</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Te'o</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name><surname>Saul</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><article-title>Molecular diversity of thermophilic cellulolytic and hemicellulolytic bacteria</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Ecol</source><year>1999</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6941.1999.tb00565.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ivanovaa</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rakhely</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovacs</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><article-title>Hydrogen production from biopolymers by <italic>Caldicellulosiruptor saccharolyticus </italic>and stabilization of the system by immobilization</article-title><source>Int J Hydrogen Energy</source><year>2008</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>6953</fpage><lpage>6961</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijhydene.2008.08.058</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kadar</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>De Vrije</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Budde</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Szengyel</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Reczey</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Claassen</surname><given-names>PAM</given-names></name><article-title>Hydrogen production from paper sludge hydrolysate</article-title><source>Appl Biochem Biotechnol</source><year>2003</year><volume>105-108</volume><fpage>557</fpage><lpage>566</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1385/ABAB:107:1-3:557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12721435</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Van Fossen</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Verhaart</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kengen</surname><given-names>SWM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><article-title>Carbohydrate utilization patterns for the extremely thermophilic bacterium <italic>Caldicellulosiruptor saccharolyticus </italic>reveal broad growth substrate preferences</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>7718</fpage><lpage>7724</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.01959-09</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>van de Werken</surname><given-names>HJG</given-names></name><name><surname>Verhaart</surname><given-names>MRA</given-names></name><name><surname>van Fossen</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Willquist</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Goorissen</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Mongodin</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>van Niel</surname><given-names>EWJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stams</surname><given-names>AJM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>de Vos</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Oost</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kengen</surname><given-names>SWM</given-names></name><article-title>Hydrogenomics of the extremely thermophilic bacterium <italic>Caldicellulosiruptor saccharolyticus</italic></article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>6720</fpage><lpage>6729</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.00968-08</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18776029</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kataeva</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sims</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Detter</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Westpheling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><article-title>Genome sequence of the anaerobic, thermophilic, and cellulolytic bacterium "Anaerocellum thermophilum" DSM 6725</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2009</year><volume>191</volume><fpage>3760</fpage><lpage>3761</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00256-09</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19346307</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kataeva</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiegel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Dam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Westpheling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>MWW</given-names></name><article-title>Reclassification of '<italic>Anaerocellum thermophilum</italic>' as <italic>Caldicellulosiruptor bescii </italic>strain DSM 6725T sp. nov</article-title><source>Int J Syst Evol Microbiol</source><year>2009</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>2011</fpage><lpage>2015</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijs.0.017731-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19801388</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sissons</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharrock</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><article-title>Isolation of cellulolytic anaerobic extreme thermophiles from New-Zealand thermal sites</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1987</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>832</fpage><lpage>838</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16347327</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Bergquist</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibbs</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Saul</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Te'o</surname><given-names>VSJ</given-names></name><person-group person-group-type="editor">Shimada K, Hoshino S, Ohmiya K, Sakka K, Kobayashi Y, Karita S</person-group><article-title>Molecular genetics of thermophilic bacterial genes coding for enzymes involved in cellulose and hemicellulose degradation</article-title><source>Genetics, biochemistry and ecology in biodegradation of lignocellulose</source><year>1993</year><publisher-name>Tokyo: Uni Publishers</publisher-name><fpage>276</fpage><lpage>285</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>van Niel</surname><given-names>EWJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Claassen</surname><given-names>PAM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stams</surname><given-names>AJM</given-names></name><article-title>Substrate and product inhibition of hydrogen production by the extreme thermophile, <italic>Caldicellulosiruptor saccharolyticus</italic></article-title><source>Biotechnol Bioeng</source><year>2003</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bit.10463</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12474247</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Willquist</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Claassen</surname><given-names>PAM</given-names></name><name><surname>van Niel</surname><given-names>EWJ</given-names></name><article-title>Evaluation of the influence of CO<sub>2 </sub>on hydrogen production by <italic>Caldicellulosiruptor saccharolyticus</italic></article-title><source>Int J Hydrogen Energy</source><year>2009</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>4718</fpage><lpage>4726</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijhydene.2009.03.056</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rainey</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Donnison</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Saul</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergquist</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stackebrandt</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><article-title>Description of <italic>Caldicellulosiruptor saccharolyticus </italic>gen-nov, sp. nov. an obligately anaerobic, extremely thermophilic, cellulolytic bacterium</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><year>1994</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6968.1994.tb07043.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8076802</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Carere</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cicek</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sparling</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Challenges for biohydrogen production via direct lignocellulose fermentation</article-title><source>Int J Hydrogen Energy</source><year>2009</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>7390</fpage><lpage>7403</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijhydene.2009.05.091</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Panagiotopoulos</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakker</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>de Vrije</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Urbaniec</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Koukios</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Claassen</surname><given-names>PAM</given-names></name><article-title>Prospects of utilization of sugar beet carbohydrates for biological hydrogen production in the EU</article-title><source>J Clean Prod</source><year>2010</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>S9</fpage><lpage>S14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2010.02.025</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ivanova</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rakhely</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovacs</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><article-title>Thermophilic biohydrogen production from energy plants by <italic>Caldicellulosiruptor saccharolyticus </italic>and comparison with related studies</article-title><source>Int J Hydrogen Energy</source><year>2009</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>3659</fpage><lpage>3670</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijhydene.2009.02.082</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cantarel</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rancurel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lombard</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Henrissat</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>The Carbohydrate-Active EnZymes database (CAZy): an expert resource for Glycogenomics</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><year>2009</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>D233</fpage><lpage>D238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkn663</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18838391</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Uyar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Eroglu</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Yucel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunduz</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><article-title>Photofermentative hydrogen production from volatile fatty acids present in dark fermentation effluents</article-title><source>Int J Hydrogen Energy</source><year>2009</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>4517</fpage><lpage>4523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijhydene.2008.07.057</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukui</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Operation of a two-stage fermentation process producing hydrogen and methane from organic waste</article-title><source>Environ Sci Technol</source><year>2007</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>1413</fpage><lpage>1419</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/es062127f</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17593750</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hallenbeck</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><article-title>Fundamentals of the fermentative production of hydrogen</article-title><source>Water Sci Technol</source><year>2005</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16180405</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Akhtar</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><article-title>Construction of a synthetic YdbK-dependent pyruvate:H<sub>2 </sub>pathway in <italic>Escherichia coli </italic>BL21(DE3)</article-title><source>Metab Eng</source><year>2009</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ymben.2009.01.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19558967</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Angenent</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Karim</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Dahhan</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Domiguez-Espinosa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Production of bioenergy and biochemicals from industrial and agricultural wastewater</article-title><source>Trends Biotechnol</source><year>2004</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>485</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tibtech.2004.07.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15331229</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kraemer</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagley</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><article-title>Supersaturation of dissolved H<sub>2 </sub>and CO<sub>2 </sub>during fermentative hydrogen production with N<sub>2 </sub>sparging</article-title><source>Biotechnol Lett</source><year>2006</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1485</fpage><lpage>1491</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10529-006-9114-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16955354</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Velt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kallm</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizutani</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><article-title>Constructing and testing the thermodynamic limits of synthetic NAD(P)H:H<sub>2 </sub>pathways</article-title><source>Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2008</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>382</fpage><lpage>394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1751-7915.2008.00033.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name><surname>Blamey</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>MWW</given-names></name><article-title>A variable-temperature direct electrochemical study of metalloproteins from hyperthermophilic microorganisms involved in hydrogen production from pyruvate</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1995</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>7161</fpage><lpage>7169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi00021a030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7766626</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Soboh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Linder</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hedderich</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>A multisubunit membrane-bound [NiFe] hydrogenase and an NADH-dependent Fe-only hydrogenase in the fermenting bacterium <italic>Thermoanaerobacter tengcongensis</italic></article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>2004</year><volume>150</volume><fpage>2451</fpage><lpage>2463</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mic.0.27159-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15256587</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schut</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>MWW</given-names></name><article-title>The iron-hydrogenase of <italic>Thermotoga maritima </italic>utilizes ferredoxin and NADH synergistically: a new perspective on anaerobic hydrogen production</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2009</year><volume>191</volume><fpage>4451</fpage><lpage>4457</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01582-08</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19411328</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Willquist</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>van Niel</surname><given-names>EWJ</given-names></name><article-title>Lactate formation in <italic>Caldicellulosiruptor saccharolyticus </italic>is regulated by the energy carriers pyrophosphate and ATP</article-title><source>Metab Eng</source><year>2010</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>282</fpage><lpage>290</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ymben.2010.01.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20060925</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Payot</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Guedon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelhaye</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Petitdemange</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Induction of lactate production associated with a decrease in NADH cell content enables growth resumption of <italic>Clostridium cellulolyticum </italic>in batch cultures on cellobiose</article-title><source>Res Microbiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>150</volume><fpage>465</fpage><lpage>473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0923-2508(99)00110-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10540910</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Abbad Andaloussi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Durr</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Raval</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Petitdemange</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Carbon and electron flow in <italic>Clostridium butyricum </italic>grown in chemostat culture on glycerol and on glucose</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>1996</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>1149</fpage><lpage>1158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/13500872-142-5-1149</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Papoutsakis</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><article-title>Increased Levels of ATP and NADH are associated with increased solvent production in continuous cultures of <italic>Clostridium acetobutylicum</italic></article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>1989</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>450</fpage><lpage>459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00263849</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kraemer</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagley</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><article-title>Improving the yield from fermentative hydrogen production</article-title><source>Biotechnol Lett</source><year>2007</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>685</fpage><lpage>695</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10529-006-9299-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17279447</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pauss</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Andre</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Guiot</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><article-title>Liquid-to-gas mass transfer in anaerobic processes: inevitable transfer limitations of methane and hydrogen in the biomethanation process</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1990</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>1636</fpage><lpage>1644</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16348206</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fiala</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Stetter</surname><given-names>KO</given-names></name><article-title><italic>Pyrococcus furiosus </italic>sp-nov represents a novel genus of marine heterotrophic archaebacteria growing optimally at 100 degrees C</article-title><source>Arch Microbiol</source><year>1986</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00413027</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mukund</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>MWW</given-names></name><article-title>Glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate ferredoxin oxidoreductase, a novel tungsten-containing enzyme with a potential glycolytic role in the hyperthermophilic archaeon <italic>Pyrococcus furiosus</italic></article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1995</year><volume>270</volume><fpage>8389</fpage><lpage>8392</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.270.15.8389</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7721730</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kengen</surname><given-names>SWM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stams</surname><given-names>AJM</given-names></name><article-title>Growth and energy conservation in batch cultures of <italic>Pyrococcus furiosus</italic></article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><year>1994</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6968.1994.tb06784.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sapra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagramyan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>MWW</given-names></name><article-title>A simple energy-conserving system: proton reduction coupled to proton translocation</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>7545</fpage><lpage>7550</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1331436100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12792025</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kengen</surname><given-names>SWM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stams</surname><given-names>AJM</given-names></name><article-title>Formation of L-alanine as a reduced end-product in carbohydrate fermentation by the hyperthermophilic archaeon <italic>Pyrococcus furiosus</italic></article-title><source>Arch Microbiol</source><year>1994</year><volume>161</volume><fpage>168</fpage><lpage>175</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00276479</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lovitt</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeikus</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><article-title>Ethanol production by thermophilic bacteria - biochemical basis for ethanol and hydrogen tolerance in <italic>Clostridium thermohydrosulfuricum</italic></article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1988</year><volume>170</volume><fpage>2809</fpage><lpage>2815</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3372483</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>MWW</given-names></name><article-title>The metabolism of hydrogen by extremely thermophilic, sulfur-dependent bacteria</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Rev</source><year>1990</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6968.1990.tb04096.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ravot</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ollivier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fardeau</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>BKC</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name><surname>Magot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><article-title>L-Alanine production from glucose fermentation by hyperthermophilic members of the domains Bacteria and Archaea: A remnant of an ancestral metabolism?</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1996</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>2657</fpage><lpage>2659</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8779604</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><article-title>Heterotrophic sulfur reduction by <italic>Thermotoga </italic>sp strain Fjss3.B1</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><year>1992</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6968.1992.tb05419.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Langworthy</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Konig</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Woese</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sleytr</surname><given-names>UB</given-names></name><name><surname>Stetter</surname><given-names>KO</given-names></name><article-title><italic>Thermotoga maritima </italic>sp. nov. represents a new genus of unique extremely thermophilic eubacteria growing up to 90 degrees Celcius</article-title><source>Arch Microbiol</source><year>1986</year><volume>144</volume><fpage>324</fpage><lpage>333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00409880</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Conners</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Montero</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shockley</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><article-title>The <italic>Thermotoga maritima </italic>phenotype is impacted by syntrophic interaction with <italic>Methanococcus jannaschii </italic>in hyperthermophilic coculture</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>811</fpage><lpage>818</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.72.1.811-818.2006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16391122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schr&#x000f6;der</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Selig</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x000f6;nheit</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Glucose fermentation to acetate, CO<sub>2 </sub>and H<sub>2 </sub>in the anaerobic hyperthermophilic eubacterium <italic>Thermotoga maritima </italic>- Involvement of the Embden-Meyerhof Pathway</article-title><source>Arch Microbiol</source><year>1994</year><volume>161</volume><fpage>460</fpage><lpage>470</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Postec</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Breton</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fardeau</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Lesongeur</surname><given-names>FO</given-names></name><name><surname>Pignet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Querellou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ollivier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Godfroy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title><italic>Marinitoga hydrogenitolerans </italic>sp nov., a novel member of the order <italic>Thermotogales </italic>isolated from a black smoker chimney on the Mid-Atlantic Ridge</article-title><source>Int J Syst Evolution Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>1217</fpage><lpage>1221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijs.0.63550-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zeidan</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>van Niel</surname><given-names>EWJ</given-names></name><article-title>A quantitative analysis of hydrogen production efficiency of the extreme thermophile <italic>Caldicellulosiruptor owensensis </italic>OLT</article-title><source>Int J Hydrogen Energy</source><year>2010</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>1128</fpage><lpage>1137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijhydene.2009.11.082</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bredholt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonne-Hansen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathrani</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahring</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><article-title><italic>Caldicellulosiruptor kristjanssonii </italic>sp nov., a cellulolytic extremely thermophilic, anaerobic bacterium</article-title><source>Int J Syst Bacteriol</source><year>1999</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>991</fpage><lpage>996</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/00207713-49-3-991</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10425755</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mandal</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Nath</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>Improvement of biohydrogen production under decreased partial pressure of H<sub>2 </sub>by <italic>Enterobacter cloacae</italic></article-title><source>Biotechnol Lett</source><year>2006</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>831</fpage><lpage>835</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10529-006-9008-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16786249</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><article-title>The ABC transporter structure and mechanism: perspectives on recent research</article-title><source>Cell Molec Life Sciences</source><year>2004</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>682</fpage><lpage>699</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00018-003-3336-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Linton</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><article-title>Structure and function of ABC transporters: the ATP switch provides flexible control</article-title><source>Pflugers Arch - Eur J Physiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>453</volume><fpage>555</fpage><lpage>567</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00424-006-0126-x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bielen</surname><given-names>AAM</given-names></name><name><surname>Willquist</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Engman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Oost</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>van Niel</surname><given-names>EWJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kengen</surname><given-names>SWM</given-names></name><article-title>Pyrophosphate as a central energy carrier in the hydrogen-producing extremely thermophilic <italic>Caldicellulosiruptor saccharolyticus</italic></article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><year>2010</year><volume>307</volume><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6968.2010.01957.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20557574</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mertens</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Pyrophosphate-dependent phosphofructokinase, an anaerobic glycolytic enzyme</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>1991</year><volume>285</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0014-5793(91)80711-B</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1648508</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ronimus</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><article-title><italic>Thermotoga maritima </italic>phosphofructokinases: expression and characterization of two unique enzymes</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2001</year><volume>183</volume><fpage>791</fpage><lpage>794</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.183.2.791-794.2001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11133978</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Heinonen</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><source>Biological role of inorganic pyrophosphate</source><year>2001</year><publisher-name>Boston/Dordrecht/London: Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B75"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brevet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fromant</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Leveque</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitter</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanquet</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Plateau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Pyrophosphatase is essential for growth of <italic>Esherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1990</year><volume>172</volume><fpage>5686</fpage><lpage>5689</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2170325</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B76"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Heinonen</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Drake</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><article-title>Comparative assessment of inorganic pyrophosphate and pyrophosphatase levels of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, <italic>Clostridium pasteurianum </italic>and <italic>Clostridium thermoaceticum</italic></article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><year>1988</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>205</fpage><lpage>208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6968.1988.tb02596.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B77"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Girbal</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Soucaille</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Regulation of <italic>Clostridium acetobutylicum </italic>metabolism as revealed by mixed-substrate steady-state continuous cultures - role of NADH/NAD ratio and ATP Pool</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1994</year><volume>176</volume><fpage>6433</fpage><lpage>6438</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7961393</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B78"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Cornish Bowden</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><source>Fundamentals of Enzyme kinetics</source><year>2004</year><edition>3</edition><publisher-name>Marseilles: Portland Press</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B79"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sode</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Makimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomiyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Construction and characterization of fermentative lactate dehydrogenase <italic>Escherichia coli </italic>mutant and its potential for bacterial hydrogen production</article-title><source>Appl Biochem Biotechnol</source><year>1999</year><volume>77-9</volume><fpage>317</fpage><lpage>323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1385/ABAB:77:1-3:317</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B80"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Burdette</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeikus</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><article-title>Purification of acetaldehyde dehydrogenase and alcohol dehydrogenases from <italic>Thermoanaerobacter ethanolicus </italic>39e and characterization of the secondary alcohol dehydrogenase (2-segrees ADH) as a bifunctional alcohol dehydrogenase acetyl-CoA reductive thioesterase</article-title><source>Biochemical J</source><year>1994</year><volume>302</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>170</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B81"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Garrigues</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Loubiere</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindley</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Cocaign-Bousquet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Control of the shift from homolactic acid to mixed-acid fermentation in <italic>Lactococcus lactis</italic>: predominant role of the NADH/NAD+ ratio</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1997</year><volume>179</volume><fpage>5282</fpage><lpage>5287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9286977</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B82"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>da Costa</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><article-title>Compatible solutes of organisms that live in hot saline environments</article-title><source>Environ Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>501</fpage><lpage>509</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1462-2920.2002.00335.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12220406</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B83"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenney</surname><given-names>FE</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>MWW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><article-title>Hydrogenesis in hyperthermophilic microorganisms: implications for biofuels</article-title><source>Metab Eng</source><year>2008</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>394</fpage><lpage>404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ymben.2008.06.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18647659</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B84"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Holst</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Manelius</surname><given-names>&#x000c5;</given-names></name><name><surname>Krahe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000e4;rkl</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Raven</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Thermophiles and fermentation technology</article-title><source>Comp BiochemPhysiol</source><year>1997</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>415</fpage><lpage>422</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B85"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawaguchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Inui</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yukawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Enhanced hydrogen production from formic acid by formate hydrogen lyase-overexpressing <italic>Escherichia coli </italic>strains</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>1716</fpage><lpage>1716</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.72.2.1716.2006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B86"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kotsopoulos</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Angelidaki</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><article-title>Biohydrogen production in granular up-flow anaerobic sludge blanket (UASB) reactors with mixed cultures under hyper-thermophilic temperature (70 degrees C)</article-title><source>Biotechnol Bioeng</source><year>2006</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>296</fpage><lpage>302</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bit.20844</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16570323</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B87"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Flemming</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><article-title>Biofilms and environmental protection</article-title><source>Water Sci Technol</source><year>1993</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B88"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Peintner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeidan</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnitzhofer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><article-title>Bioreactor systems for thermophilic fermentative hydrogen production: evaluation and comparison of appropriate systems</article-title><source>J Cleaner Prod</source></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B89"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lynd</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>van Zyl</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>McBride</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Laser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Consolidated bioprocessing of cellulosic biomass: an update</article-title><source>Curr Opin Biotechnol</source><year>2005</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>577</fpage><lpage>583</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.copbio.2005.08.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16154338</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B90"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Verhaart</surname><given-names>MRA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bielen</surname><given-names>AAM</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Oost</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stams</surname><given-names>AJM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kengen</surname><given-names>SWM</given-names></name><article-title>Hydrogen production by hyperthermophilic and extremely thermophilic bacteria and archaea: mechanisms for reductant disposal</article-title><source>EnvironTechnol</source><year>2010</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>993</fpage><lpage>1003</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B91"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tanisho</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wakao</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><article-title>Fermentative hydrogen evolution by <italic>Enterobacter aerogenes </italic>strain E-82005</article-title><source>Int J Hydrogen Energy</source><year>1987</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>623</fpage><lpage>627</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0360-3199(87)90003-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B92"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>Continuous hydrogen production by immobilized <italic>Enterobacter cloacae </italic>IIT-BT 08 using lignocellulosic materials as solid matrices</article-title><source>Enzyme Microbiol Technol</source><year>2001</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>280</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0141-0229(01)00394-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B93"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kataoka</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Miya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiriyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>Studies on hydrogen production by continuous culture system of hydrogen-producing anaerobic bacteria</article-title><source>Water Sci Technol</source><year>1997</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>47</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B94"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><article-title>Fedbatch operation using <italic>Clostridium acetobutylicum </italic>suspension culture as biocatalyst for enhancing hydrogen production</article-title><source>Biotechnol Prog</source><year>2003</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>383</fpage><lpage>388</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bp0200604</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12675576</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B95"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><article-title>Electrotransformation of <italic>Thermoanaerobacter ethanolicus </italic>JW200</article-title><source>Biotechnol Lett</source><year>2006</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1913</fpage><lpage>1917</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10529-006-9184-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16988780</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B96"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukui</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Atomi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Imanaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><article-title>Improved and versatile transformation system allowing multiple genetic manipulations of the hyperthermophilic archaeon <italic>Thermococcus kodakaraensis</italic></article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>3889</fpage><lpage>3899</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.71.7.3889-3899.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16000802</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B97"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Santangelo</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cubonova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Reeve</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><article-title>Shuttle vector expression in Thermococcus kodakaraensis: contributions of cis elements to protein synthesis in a hyperthermophilic archaeon</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>3099</fpage><lpage>3104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.00305-08</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18378640</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B98"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tyurin</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynd</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><article-title>Electrotransformation of <italic>Clostridium thermocellum</italic></article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>883</fpage><lpage>890</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.70.2.883-890.2004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14766568</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B99"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Conners</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Montero</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name><surname>Comfort</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shockley</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chhabra</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><article-title>An expression-driven approach to the prediction of carbohydrate transport and utilization regulons in the hyperthermophilic bacterium <italic>Thermotoga maritima</italic></article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2005</year><volume>187</volume><fpage>7267</fpage><lpage>7282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.187.21.7267-7282.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16237010</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B100"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhatnagar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>An analysis of the proteomic profile for <italic>Thermoanaerobacter tengcongensis </italic>under optimal culture conditions</article-title><source>Proteomics</source><year>2004</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>136</fpage><lpage>150</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pmic.200300504</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14730678</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B101"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Weekes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaroszewski</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginalski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Deacon</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wooley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lesley</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Osterman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Godzik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Three-dimensional structural view of the central metabolic network of <italic>Thermotoga maritima</italic></article-title><source>Science</source><year>2009</year><volume>325</volume><fpage>1544</fpage><lpage>1549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1174671</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19762644</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B102"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Gowen</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Fong</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><article-title>Genome-scale metabolic analysis of <italic>Clostridium thermocellum </italic>for bioethanol production</article-title><source>BMC Syst Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>31</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1752-0509-4-31</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20307315</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B103"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bothun</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Knutson</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Berberich</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Strobel</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nokes</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><article-title>Metabolic selectivity and growth of <italic>Clostridium thermocellum </italic>in continuous culture under elevated hydrostatic pressure</article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2004</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-004-1554-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14752579</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B104"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Munro</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zinder</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><article-title>The fermentation stoichiometry of <italic>Thermotoga neapolitana </italic>and influence of temperature, oxygen, and pH on hydrogen production</article-title><source>Biotechnol Prog</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1035</fpage><lpage>1042</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/btpr.201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19551880</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B105"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hild</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuckey</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Leak</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><article-title>Effect of nutrient limitation on product formation during continuous fermentation of xylose with <italic>Thermoanaerobacter ethanolicus </italic>JW200 Fe(7)</article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2003</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>679</fpage><lpage>686</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12664146</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B106"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kanai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Imanaka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Uwamori</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Omori</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukui</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Atomi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Imanaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><article-title>Continuous hydrogen production by the hyperthermophilic archaeon, <italic>Thermococcus kodakaraensis </italic>KOD1</article-title><source>J Biotechnol</source><year>2005</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbiotec.2004.11.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15707688</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B107"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>de Souza</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sutherland</surname><given-names>IW</given-names></name><article-title>Exopolysaccharide and storage polymer production in <italic>Enterobacter aerogenes </italic>type-8 strains</article-title><source>J Appl Bacteriol</source><year>1994</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>463</fpage><lpage>468</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B108"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hutkins</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kashket</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><article-title>Phosphotransferase activity in <italic>Clostridium acetobutylicum </italic>from acidogenic and solventogenic phases of growth</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1986</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>1121</fpage><lpage>1123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16347058</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B109"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><article-title>Transport of D-glucose in <italic>Clostridium thermocellum </italic>ATCC-27405</article-title><source>J Gen Appl Microbiol</source><year>1982</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>469</fpage><lpage>477</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2323/jgam.28.469</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B110"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Galperin</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Noll</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><article-title>The glucose transport system of the hyperthermophilic anaerobic bacterium <italic>Thermotoga neapolitana</italic></article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1996</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>2915</fpage><lpage>2918</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9285772</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>