<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Zookeys</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>ZooKeys</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21998516</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3192425</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.119.1451</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Color variability and body size of larvae of two <italic>Epomis</italic> species (Coleoptera, Carabidae) in Israel, with a key to the larval stages</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wizen</surname><given-names>Gil</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gasith</surname><given-names>Avital</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label/>Tel Aviv University, George S. Wise Faculty of Life Sciences, Department of Zoology, The National Collections of Natural History, Tel-Aviv 69978, Israel</aff><author-notes><corresp>Corresponding author: Gil Wizen (<email>wizentrop@gmail.com</email>).</corresp><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Academic editor: Achille Casale</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>7</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><issue>119</issue><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>4</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>7</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Gil Wizen, Avital Gasith</copyright-statement><license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><label>Abstract</label><p>Species identification using the characteristics of developmental stages is challenging. However, for insect taxonomy the coloration of larval stages can be an informative feature. The use of live specimens is recommended for this because the color fades in preserved specimens. In this study we examine the possibility of using variation in coloration and color pattern of larvae in order to distinguish between twoground beetlesspecies <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis dejeani</named-content></italic> (Dejean, 1831) and <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis circumscriptus</named-content></italic> (Duftschmid, 1812). We present an atlas and describe the coloration and body size of the three larval stages of the above species based on live specimens. An identification key is given for the three larval instars of the two <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic> species.</p><p>The first instar larvae of the two <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic> species can be easily distinguished based on their color. From the second instar on, the variability in coloration and color patterns increases, creating an overlap in these attributes between larvae of the two species. Except for minor differences in color of the antennae and the base of the mandibles, larvae of the two species are indistinguishable at the second and third larval stages. To the best of our knowledge this is the first attempt to use variation in coloration and color pattern in live larvae in order to identify coleopterans. The color atlas of the larvae enables simple separation of the two <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic> species without requiring sophisticated magnifying devices, although it is less straightforward at the second and third larval stages.</p><p>We found similar body lengths between the two species for all developmental stages, except for third instar larvae prior to pupation. In the two species the difference in larval body length before pupation positively correlated with that of the adult beetles. More than 70% of the adults&#x02019; length can be explained by the length of the late third-instar larva; i.e. the large larvae develop into large adults. The larger specimens are the females.</p></abstract><kwd-group><label>Keywords</label><kwd><italic>Epomis</italic> larvae</kwd><kwd>Carabidae</kwd><kwd>color atlas</kwd><kwd>body size</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Coloration can be an informative feature for insect taxonomy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">van Emden 1957</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Luff 1993</xref>). While the larvae of some ground beetles (<named-content content-type="taxon-name">Carabidae</named-content>) have been well studied (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Lawrence 1991</xref>) for other beetles the larval stage is still unknown. Those larvae that have been studied were described according to morphology and structure, with less attention paid to color (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">van Emden 1942</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Thompson 1979</xref>). Of the latter descriptions, some give limited information about the color of ground beetle larvae (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">van Emden 1942</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Thompson 1979</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Luff 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Erwin and Medina 2003</xref>), but not on pattern and color variability. Information available so far indicates that generally color variability in <named-content content-type="taxon-name">Coleoptera</named-content> larvae is rare and so is the case in ground beetle larvae as well (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Luff 1993</xref>, senior author personal observations).</p><p>In a recent study of two <named-content content-type="taxon-name">Chlaeniini</named-content> (<named-content content-type="taxon-name">Carabidae</named-content>) species of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic>, <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis dejeani</named-content></italic> (Dejean, 1831) and <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis circumscriptus</named-content></italic> (Duftschmid, 1812), in Israel, we noticed that the larvae display color variation. The genus <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic> Bonelli, 1810 consists in ca. 20 species, mostly known from tropical Africa and south and south eastern Asia. Five of the species are from the Palaearctic region (Kryzhanovskij 1983). In mediterranean lands in Europe, this genus is rare and considered endangered (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Brandmayr and Algieri 2000</xref>). <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic> have three larval stages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Elron et al. 2007</xref>). The third instar larva of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis dejeani</named-content></italic> was first described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Makarova (2005)</xref>. Recently, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Brandmayr et al. (2010)</xref> added a description of the first instar of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis dejeani</named-content></italic> and of the first and third instar larvae of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis circumscriptus</named-content></italic>. In none of the above morphological descriptions, however, is color variation in the larvae mentioned. This may be partly attributed to examination of larvae preserved in formaldehyde and alcohol. Preservation results in fading of the coloration of soft-bodied insects, particularly of the immature stages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">McFarland 1964</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Moore 1971</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Luff 1993</xref>).</p><p>The taxonomic status of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic> is under debate. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Kirschenhofer (2003)</xref> considers <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic> as a subgenus of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Chlaenius</named-content></italic>, whereas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Basilewsky (1955)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Makarova (2005)</xref> consider it as a separate genus. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Brandmayr et al. (2010)</xref>, who examined and described the larvae of the two discussed species, support the separate standing of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic> as a genus. Here we adopt the latter taxonomic approach.</p><p>We describe the variation in coloration and color pattern and body size of the three larval stages of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis dejeani</named-content></italic> and <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis circumscriptus</named-content></italic>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods<!--PageBreak--></title><p>The three larval stages of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic> are referred to as L1, L2 and L3. Larvae were obtained <italic>ex-ovo</italic> in the laboratory from a dozen females of each species collected in the wild. The two <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic> species do not coexist at the same sites. Adults of each species were collected in a different locality from the largest population known for each species. The larvae were reared in a room with constant temperature (25oC &#x000b1; 1oC) and artificial light. They were kept in one liter plastic containers (10.5 cm high; 14.5 cm diameter) with moist peat as substrate and were fed with live amphibian metamorphs. Freshly hatched or molted larvae appear uniformly white; the final color appears after about two hours. For this reason we used larvae 10 hours after hatching or 10 hours post-molt for documenting color variability and patterns. We photographed them using a Canon EOS 50D camera with Canon MP-E 65 mm and EF-S 60 mm macro lenses and Canon MT-24EX flash. We also measured larval body length from the tip of the mandible to the end of the abdomen (mandible-abdomen length, MAL) using a caliper (&#x000b1;0.05 mm). L1 was measured after hatching and before molting into L2; L2 was measured after molting and before molting into L3; and L3 was measured after molting and before pupation. We measured the body length of the adults that emerged (from the tip of the mandible to the end of the elytra), and examined the correlation between their body length with that of the late L3.</p><p>The statistical analysis was performed using Statistica ver. 8. Due to a small sample size and non-normal distribution of the data we used non-parametric statistical tests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Zar 1998</xref>). For comparing body lengths of each larval instar between the two species we used Mann-Whitney test. For analyzing the relationship of pre-pupation, third instar body length with the respective body length of the emerged adult we used Spearman correlation.</p><p>We prepared a key to the larvae, incorporating morphological characters described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Brandmayr et al. (2010)</xref> with the color characteristics and body length information recorded in this study. The description by Brandmayer et al. is based to a large degree on larvae we provided the senior author. Those larvae were from the same populations described above and were obtained in the same manner.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec sec-type="Coloration and body length of E. dejeani larvae"><title>Coloration and body length of E. dejeani larvae</title><p>L1, L2 and L3 differ in coloration. Moreover, we found variability in coloration within L2 and L3 stages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>). Median mandible-abdomen length (MAL) of L1 after hatching is 4.8 mm and before molting into L2 it is 8.3 mm (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). The larva is mostly black-dark brown, with the last two or three segments of the abdomen being yellow. The tergite preceding the latter segments is medially yellow and its sides are black. The base of the mandible is pale brown or pale yellow. The retinaculum is reddish-brown and the apex is of similar but paler color. The remaining mouthparts, antennae, legs and urogomphi are pale yellow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Median MAL of L2 after molting is 8.3 mm and before molting into L3 it is 13.2 mm (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). The main body color of <!--PageBreak-->L2 ranges from pale brown with black spots to completely black. The legs and urogomphi are pale yellow and sometimes their base is black. The mandibles are pale brown or black, apex and retinaculum are reddish-brown. The base of the mandible is pale brown. The remaining mouthparts and antennae are pale brown or grey (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>). Median MAL of L3 after molting is 13.5 mm and before pupation it is 18.2 mm (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). L3 resembles L2 in coloration, with the main body color ranging from pale brown with black spots to completely black. The legs are pale yellow. The urogomphi are mostly pale yellow but in dark colored larvae the base of the urogomphi is black. The mandibles are pale brown or black, apex and retinaculum are reddish-brown. The base of the mandible is pale brown. The remaining mouthparts and antennae are pale brown or grey (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Morphs presenting color variability of L1 larvae of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis dejeani</named-content></italic>.Scale bar 2 mm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-119-037-g001"/></fig><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Morphs presenting color variability of L2 larvae of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis dejeani</named-content></italic>. Scale bar 5 mm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-119-037-g002"/></fig><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Morphs presenting color variability of L3 larvae of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis dejeani</named-content></italic>.Scale bar 10 mm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-119-037-g003"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Median body length (mm) of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis dejeani</named-content></italic> and <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis circumscriptus</named-content></italic> larvae and inter-species MAL comparison (Mann-Whitney test) at different developmental stages. Number in parentheses indicates number of individuals.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Taxa</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="2">L1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="2">L2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="2">L3</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">After hatching</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prior to molting </th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">After molting</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prior to molting </th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">After molting</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prior to pupation</th></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E. dejeani</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8 (12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3 (12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3 (10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.2 (10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.5 (12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.2 (11)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E. circumscriptus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5 (9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.9 (10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.2 (14)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.102</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.522</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.088</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.595</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.542</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00084</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="Coloration and body length of E. circumscriptus larvae"><title>Coloration and body length of E. circumscriptus larvae</title><p>L1, L2 and L3 differ in coloration. Here too we found variability in coloration within L2 and L3 stages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>). Median MAL of L1 after hatching is 5 mm and before molting into L2 it is 8.5 mm (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). The larva L1 is mostly pale yellow or brownish and on rare occasions brown. In some larvae the sides of the body are grayish-black. The apex and retinaculum are reddish. The remaining mouthparts, antennae, legs and urogomphi are pale yellow. The dark eyes are prominent against the background of the brighter body (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). Median MAL of L2 after molting is 8.9 mm and before molting into L3 it is 13 mm (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). The main body color ranges from yellow-brown or white with black and orange spots to completely black with orange spots. The legs and urogomphi are yellow. The mandibles are black, apex and retinaculum are red. The remaining mouthparts are grey or black. The antennae are mostly black except for the two apical segments which are pale yellow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>). Median MAL of L3 after molting is 14 mm and before pupation it is 20.2 mm (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). The main body color ranges from dark brown or white with black and orange spots to completely black with orange spots. On rare occasions the orange spots are missing. The legs and urogomphi are yellow. The mandibles are black, apex and retinaculum are<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--> reddish-brown. The remaining mouthparts are grey or black. The antennae are mostly black except for the two last segments which are pale yellow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>).</p><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Morphs presenting color variability of L1 larvae of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis circumscriptus</named-content></italic>. Scale bar 2 mm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-119-037-g004"/></fig><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Morphs presenting color variability of L2 larvae of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis circumscriptus</named-content></italic>.Scale bar 5 mm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-119-037-g005"/></fig><fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Morphs presenting color variability of L3 larvae of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis circumscriptus</named-content></italic>. Scale bar 10 mm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-119-037-g006"/></fig><fig id="F7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Head (dorsal view) of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic> larvae showing differences in color of antennae and base of mandibles between the two species <bold>a</bold> <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis dejeani</named-content></italic>, L2 dark morph <bold>b</bold> <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis dejeani</named-content></italic>, L3 pale morph <bold>c</bold> <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis circumscriptus</named-content></italic>, L2 dark morph <bold>d</bold> <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis circumscriptus</named-content></italic>, L3 pale morph. Scale bar 2 mm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-119-037-g007"/></fig><p>Except for L3 before pupation, the body length of L1, L2 and L3 of the two <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic> species is similar (Mann-Whitney, p&#x0003e;0.09, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Prior to pupation the body length <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis circumscriptus</named-content></italic> L3 is larger than that of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis dejeani</named-content></italic> at the same larval stage (Mann-Whitney, p&#x0003c;0.001; <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="Relationship between pre-pupal instar and adult body length"><title>Relationship between pre-pupal instar and adult body length</title><p>For each species we compared body length of pre-pupal instar to that of the adult that emerged (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). We found a positive significant correlation between larval and ad<!--PageBreak-->ult body length in each of the two species (Spearman correlation; p&#x02264;0.005). Larger larvae metamorphosed into larger adults. Larval size explains 72 and 82% of the variability in adult length in <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis dejeani</named-content></italic> and <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis circumscriptus</named-content></italic>, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref>). The largest larvae developed into females.</p><fig id="F8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Correlation between adults&#x02019; body length (mm) and that of third-instar larvae (mm) of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis dejeani</named-content></italic> males (open circles) and females (black circles). Regression equation and coefficient of variation are shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-119-037-g008"/></fig><fig id="F9" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Correlation between adults&#x02019; body length (mm) and that of third-instar larvae (mm) of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis circumscriptus</named-content></italic> males (open circles) and females (black circles). Regression equation and coefficient of variation are shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-119-037-g009"/></fig><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Range and median of body length (mm) of third instar larvae before pupation and of adults (male and female) of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis dejeani</named-content></italic> and <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis circumscriptus</named-content></italic>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">Taxa</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="4">Body length (mm)</th><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">Sex</th><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">Individual number</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="2">L3 before pupation</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="2">Adult</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">range</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">median</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">range</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">median</th></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">E. dejeani</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x02013;18.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.5&#x02013;17.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.2&#x02013;20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.8&#x02013;18.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">E. circumscriptus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#x02013;20.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.9&#x02013;19.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.4&#x02013;27.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.8&#x02013;21.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p><!--PageBreak--><bold>Key to the larvae</bold></p><table-wrap content-type="key" orientation="portrait" id="d33e760" position="anchor"><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body length of the larva is up to 8.5 mm; egg bursters present on forehead, consisting of two rows of denticles; first instar</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body length of the larva is larger than 8.5 mm; no egg bursters present</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body length is 5 to 8.5 mm; color is mostly pale yellow or brownish, sometimes brown; body sides can sometimes be grayish-black; mandibles&#x02019; color is similar to body color, apex and retinaculum are darker and reddish; retinaculum on the same plane as the apical tooth and about the same length as the latter; both teeth strongly chitinized and curved, forming a strong double complanar hook; the remaining mouthparts, antennae, legs and urogomphi are pale yellow; stemmata are dark and clearly visible against the bright body color (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis circumscriptus</named-content></italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body length is 4.8 to 8.3 mm; color is mostly black-dark brown, the last two or three segments of the abdomen are yellow, the tergite preceding these segments is medially yellow with black sides; mandible base is pale brown or pale yellow, retinaculum reddish-brown and apex of similar but paler color; retinaculum as robust as the apex, bent dorsally and backwards, not at the same plain as the apex, especially on the left side; both teeth strongly chitinized and curved, forming a strong double hook; the remaining mouthparts, antennae, legs and urogomphi are pale yellow; stemmata are poorly pigmented (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis dejeani</named-content></italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body length of the larva is up to 13.5 mm; second instar</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body length of the larva is larger than 13.5 mm; third instar</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body length is 8.9 to 13.5 mm; color ranges from yellow-brown or white with black and orange spots to uniformly black with orange spots; the mandibles are black, apex and retinaculum are red; the remaining mouthparts are grey or black; the antennae are mostly black except for the two apical segments which are pale yellow; legs and urogomphi are yellow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis circumscriptus</named-content></italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body length is 8.3 to 13.2 mm; color ranges from pale brown with black spots to uniformly black; the mandibles are pale brown or black, mandible base is pale brown, apex and retinaculum are reddish-brown; the remaining mouthparts and antennae are pale brown or grey; legs and urogomphi are pale yellow, urogomphi sometimes black at base (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis dejeani</named-content></italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body length is 14 to 20.2 mm; color ranges from dark brown or white with black and orange spots to uniformly black with or without orange spots; the mandibles are black, apex and retinaculum are reddish-brown; the remaining mouthparts are grey or black; the antennae are mostly black with the two last segments which are yellow; legs and urogomphi are yellow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis circumscriptus</named-content></italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body length is 13.5 to 18.2 mm; color ranges from pale brown with black spots to uniformly black; the mandibles are pale brown or black, mandible base is pale brown, apex and retinaculum are reddish-brown; the remaining<!--PageBreak--> mouthparts and antennae are pale brown or grey; legs pale yellow; urogomphi mostly pale yellow, and with a black base in uniformly black colored larvae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis dejeani</named-content></italic></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p><italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis dejeani</named-content></italic> and <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis circumscriptus</named-content></italic> appear in the key to European <named-content content-type="taxon-name">Carabidae</named-content> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Trautner and Geigenm&#x000fc;ller 1987</xref>), which uses characters associated with identification of adults only. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Makarova (2005)</xref> described for the first time the third-instar larva of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis dejeani</named-content></italic> (preserved specimen). We recently sent all three larval stages of the two <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic> species known from Israel to Pietro Brandmayr (University of Calabria, Italy) for description (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Brandmayr et al. 2010</xref>). Brandmayr et al. reported a clear difference in mandible morphology in the first instar larvae of the two species. In <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis dejeani</named-content></italic> larvae the retinaculum is bent dorsally while the apex is bent medially, whereas in <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis circumscriptus</named-content></italic> larvae both retinaculum and apex are bent medially. A preliminary description of coloration of preserved larvae (in 70% alcohol) of the first and third larval stages is given. While studying the <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic> larvae we noticed that the color of preserved larvae fades with time, making color descriptions based on preserved specimens problematic. Here we present data on developmental changes reflected in variation in coloration and color pattern of the three larval stages, as well as body size. This is based on live specimens reared in the laboratory under the same conditions.</p><p>We found variability in color patterns in all larval stages of the two <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic> species. A couple of hours after hatching the first instar larvae of the two species can be easily distinguished based on their color. From the second instar on, the variability in coloration and color patterns increases, creating an overlap in these characteristics between larvae of the two species. Except for minor differences in color of the antennae and the base of the mandibles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>), larvae of the two species are indistinguishable at the second and third larval stages. We found no significant difference in body length of larvae of the two <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic> species, except for the third instar larvae prior to pupation. At this stage the median body length of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis circumscriptus</named-content></italic> larvae is 2 mm longer than that of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis dejeani</named-content></italic> at the same stage. In the two species the difference in larval body length before pupation positively correlated with that of the adult beetles.</p><p><italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic> adults are the largest among the <named-content content-type="taxon-name">Chlaeniini</named-content> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Basilewsky 1955</xref>). Here we found that in both <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic> species more than 70% of the adults&#x02019; length can be explained by the length of the late third instar larva; therefore, the large larvae develop into large adults. The larger specimens were the females. Although we have no additional evidence for a similar correlation between larval and adult body length in other carabids, this phenomenon is known from other <named-content content-type="taxon-name">Coleoptera</named-content> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Stern and Emlen 1999</xref>).</p><p>According to the Catalogue of Palaearctic <named-content content-type="taxon-name">Coleoptera</named-content> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Kirschenhofer 2003</xref>) and the key to the European <named-content content-type="taxon-name">Carabidae</named-content> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Trautner and Geigenm&#x000fc;ller 1987</xref>), <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic> is a subge<!--PageBreak-->nus of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Chlaenius</named-content></italic>, and adults of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic> are distinguished from their close <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Chlaenius</named-content></italic> relatives in their larger body length and the shape of their labial palp (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Trautner and Geigenm&#x000fc;ller 1987</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Basilewsky (1955)</xref> examined the African fauna of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic> and published a revision calling for separation of the genera. The description of the third instar larva of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis dejeani</named-content></italic> supports this conclusion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Makarova 2005</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Brandmayr et al. (2010)</xref>, who examined and described the larvae of the two species discussed in this study, also support the separate standing of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic> as a genus within the <named-content content-type="taxon-name">Chlaeniini</named-content> tribe. New data on the life history of the <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic> larvae (Wizen G and Gasith A, unpublished manuscript) indicate a unique biology of the <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic> beetles and therefore support the latter conclusion.</p><p>It should be pointed out that <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic> is an endangered taxon in the European Mediterranean region. <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis circumscriptus</named-content></italic> was classified as a critically endangered species in Italy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Brandmayr and Algieri 2000</xref>). In Israel, <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic> populations are small and sparsely distributed. These findings and the fact that the larvae depends on a food source that is declining in many parts of the world (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Alford and Richards 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Blaustein and Kiesecker 2002</xref>) suggests special attention for conservation measures that should be taken in order to protect these beetles from extinction.</p><p>In conclusion, the color atlas of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic> larvae that we provide present the color pattern of yet little known larval stages of two ground beetle species, moreover it enables a simple separation of the two species without requiring sophisticated magnifying devices (for example ESM). The two species are easily distinguishable at the first larval stage. While the separation is less straightforward at the later stages, it is nonetheless possible by focusing on the color of the antennae and base of the mandibles. Accurate identification requires use of additional taxonomic tools. In another study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Settanni et al. 2009</xref>) the researchers used differential coloration of tergites in first instar larvae of two <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Berberomeloe</named-content></italic> species (<named-content content-type="taxon-name">Meloidae</named-content>, <named-content content-type="taxon-name">Coleoptera</named-content>) as diagnostic character for identification. However, their results rely on preserved specimens. To the best of our knowledge this is the first attempt to use variation in coloration and color pattern in live larvae in order to identify coleopterans.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank Pietro Brandmayr and Tullia Zetto-Brandmayr (University of Calabria, Italy) for describing the larvae and for constructive remarks. We thank Thorsten Assman (Leuphana University, Germany) for providing information on past taxonomic status of <italic><named-content content-type="taxon-name">Epomis</named-content></italic>. Alex Shlagman (Department of Zoology, Tel-Aviv University, Israel) provided essential information on larvae rearing. We are indebted to Naomi Paz (Tel-Aviv University) for editorial assistance. Permit for collecting and rearing the beetles was issued by the Nature and Parks Authority, Israel.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References<!--PageBreak--></title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Alford</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> Global amphibian declines: a problem in applied ecology.</article-title><source>Annual Review of Ecology and Systematics </source><volume>30</volume>: <fpage>133</fpage>-<lpage>165</lpage> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.ecolsys.30.1.133">doi:10.1146/annurev.ecolsys.30.1.133</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Basilewsky</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1955</year>)<article-title> R&#x000e9;vision des ep&#x000e8;ces africaines du genre <italic>Epomis</italic> (Carabidae).</article-title><source>Transactions of the Royal Entomological Society of London</source><volume>107</volume>: <fpage>95</fpage>-<lpage>116</lpage> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2311.1955.tb00466.x">doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2311.1955.tb00466.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Blaustein</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiesecker</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Complexity in conservation: lessons from the global decline of amphibian population.</article-title><source>Ecology Letters </source><volume>5</volume>: <fpage>597</fpage>-<lpage>608</lpage> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.1461-0248.2002.00352.x">doi: 10.1046/j.1461-0248.2002.00352.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Brandmayr</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Algieri</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Habitat affinities of Chlaeniine species (Coleoptera, Carabidae) in Calabria and the status of <italic>Epomis circumscriptus</italic>, evaluated by the &#x0201c;<italic>Cronogeonemie</italic>&#x0201d; software.</article-title> In: <person-group><name><surname>Brandmayr et</surname><given-names>al</given-names></name></person-group> <issue-title> (Eds) Natural History and Applied Ecology of Carabid Beetles. Proceedings of the 9th European Carabidologists Meeting, July 1988, Camigliatello, Cosenza (Italy).</issue-title><source>Pensoft, Series Faunistica </source><volume>19</volume>: <fpage>71</fpage>-<lpage>78</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Brandmayr</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonacci</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zetto-Brandmayr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Larval morphology of <italic>Epomis circumscriptus</italic> (Duftschmid 1812) and of first instar <italic>Epomis dejeani</italic>, Dejean, 1831, (Coleoptera, Carabidae, Chlaeniini), with morphofunctional remarks.</article-title><source>Zootaxa </source><volume>2388</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>-<lpage>58</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Elron</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Shlagman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasith</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> First detailed report of predation on anuran metamorphs by terrestrial beetle larvae.</article-title><source>Herpetological Review </source><volume>38</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>30</fpage>-<lpage>33</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Emden FI</surname><given-names>van</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1942</year>)<article-title> A key to the genera of larval Carabidae (Col.).</article-title><source>Transactions of the Royal Entomological Society of London</source><volume>92</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>99</lpage> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2311.1942.tb03318.x">doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2311.1942.tb03318.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Emden FI</surname><given-names>van</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1957</year>)<article-title> The Taxonomic Significance of the Characters of Immature Insects.</article-title><source>Annual Review of Entomology </source><volume>2</volume>: <fpage>91</fpage>-<lpage>106</lpage> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.en.02.010157.000515">doi: 10.1146/annurev.en.02.010157.000515</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Erwin</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Medina</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> The neotropical species <italic>Askalaphium depressum</italic> (Bates): Larval description, first diagnosis and illustrations of immature Ctenodactylini, with natural history notes on the genus and tribe (Coleoptera: Carabidae).</article-title><source>Zootaxa </source><volume>273</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>15</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group><name><surname>Kirschenhofer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Tribe Chlaeniini Brull&#x000e9;, 1834.</article-title> In: <person-group><name><surname>L&#x000f6;bl</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Smetana</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Catalogue of Palaearctic Coleoptera, Vol.</issue-title><source>1: Archostemata, Myxophaga, Adephaga. Apollo Books, Stenstrup</source>: <fpage>347</fpage>-<lpage>356</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Order Coleoptera (general discussion, family key, many family treatments)</article-title>. In: <person-group><name><surname>Stehr</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed&#x0003e;</role>) <source>Immature Insects, Vol. 2</source>. <publisher-name>Kendall/HuntPublishing Co</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Dubuque, IA</publisher-loc>, <fpage>144</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>658</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><name><surname>Luff</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<source> The Carabidae (Coleoptera) larvae of Fennoscandia and Denmark. Fauna Entomologica Scandinavica, vol. 27.</source><publisher-name>Scandinavian Science Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Leiden, Copenhagen</publisher-loc>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>186</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Makarova</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> The larva of the ground beetle <italic>Epomis dejeani</italic> (Coleoptera, Carabidae).</article-title><source>Entomological Review </source><volume>85</volume>: <fpage>100</fpage>-<lpage>106</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>McFarland</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1964</year>)<article-title> Notes on collecting, rearing and preserving larvae of Macrolepidoptera.</article-title><source>Journal of The Lepidopterists&#x02019; Society </source><volume>18</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>201</fpage>-<lpage>210</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1971</year>)<article-title> Notes on an extraordinary blood-feeding carabid larva (Coleoptera) from Port Elizabeth.</article-title><source>Annual of the Natal Museum </source><volume>20</volume>: <fpage>479</fpage>-<lpage>482</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Settanni</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Giulio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Finoia</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bologna</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Intra- and interspecific analysis of first instar larval morphology in the genus Berberomeloe Bologna 1989 (Coleoptera: Meloidae).</article-title><source>Zootaxa </source><volume>2089</volume>: <fpage>52</fpage>-<lpage>64</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group><name><surname>Shiina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tachikawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>)<article-title> The life history of <italic>Epomis nigricans</italic> and its larval stage feeding on toads</article-title>. <source>Abstracts of the 48th Annual Meetingof the Entomological Society of Japan, Nishibaru, Okinawa</source>, <lpage>35</lpage> (in Japanese).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Emlen</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> The developmental basis for allometry in insects.</article-title><source>Development </source><volume>126</volume>: <fpage>1091</fpage>-<lpage>1101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10021329</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><name><surname>Tachikawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<article-title> Predation on anurans by <italic>Epomis nigricans</italic> larvae</article-title>. In: <source>Amazing Life of Insects, Atlas of the 48th Special Exhibition</source>, <publisher-name>Otaru Museum</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Otaru</publisher-loc>, <lpage>20</lpage> (in Japanese).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>Larvae of North American Carabidae with a key to the tribes</article-title>. In: <person-group><name><surname>Erwin</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitehead</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Halpern</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Carabid Beetles: Their Evolution, Natural History, and Classification</source>. <publisher-loc>The Hague</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>W. Junk</publisher-name>, <fpage>209</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>291</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><name><surname>Trautner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Geigenm&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>)<source> Tiger Beetles, Ground Beetles: Illustrated Keys to the Cicindelidae and Carabidae of Europe.</source><publisher-name>Aichtal</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Josef Margraf</publisher-loc>, <lpage>487</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><name><surname>Zar</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<source> Biostatistical Analysis (4th Edition).</source><publisher-name>Prentice Hall, Englewood Clifs</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New Jersey</publisher-loc>, <lpage>929</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>